<folder xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions"
        xmlns:uuid="java:java.util.UUID"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <Title>Document</Title>
   <folder ptx="chapter" xml:id="engineering-measurement">
      <Title>Engineering Measurement</Title>
      <item>
         <objectives>
            <ul>
               <li>Understand the units of measurement for length, mass, time, area, volume, speed, temperature, pressure, torque, power, and speed</li>
               <li>Understand conversions from U.S to metric and metric to U.S.</li>
               <li>Understand Nautical Mile definition</li>
               <li>Be able to calculate conversions</li>
               <li>Identify and draw standard measurement symbols</li>
               <li>Understand basic measuring instruments</li>
               <li>Understand accuracy, precision, tolerance, calibration</li>
            </ul>
         </objectives>
      </item>
      <folder ptx="introduction">
         <Title>introduction</Title>
         <item>
            <p>Measurement is the process of associating numbers with quantities. Units of measurement establish a common language for engineers to communicate and quantify various physical quantities. There are two basic standard units of measurement systems that are used worldwide, the U.S. Standard Measurement System and the Metric System.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In the world of engineering, measurement is fundamental. Accurate measurements are crucial for designing, constructing, and evaluating systems. Engineers rely on standardized units and principles of measurement to ensure consistency and precision in their work.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>This chapter provides an overview of the categories and units of measurement used in engineering systems, covering both the metric and US standard systems as well as nautical measurement. An overview of basic instruments used for making measurements will be discussed along with the principles of measurement <term>including</term> accuracy, efficiency, percent error and deviation.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>As you study this chapter, you will encounter new terms and definitions for you to learn. At the end of the chapter, you will find example problems. Be sure to take the time to practice with these problems. They will help prepare you to apply these concepts. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="engineering-measurement-length">
         <Title>Length</Title>
         <folder ptx="subsection" xml:id="engineering-measurement-a-brief-history">
            <Title>A Brief History</Title>
            <item>
               <p>The way base units of length have been determined has changed greatly over time. Long ago, the base for reference was the human body. For example, the cubit was a unit that indicated the length from the elbow to the fingertips.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Length units based on the human body were used for thousands of years. The Roman mile (In Latin <foreign>mille passus </foreign>, which means <q>thousand paces</q>) consisted of a thousand paces (of 5 feet each) as measured by every other step—as in the total distance of the left foot hitting the ground 1,000 times, which equals approximately 5,000 ft. In 1592, English Parliament wanted to standardize the measurement of the mile and made the decision that it should be equal to eight furlongs. Furlongs, which are still used as a unit of measurement in horse racing, are 660 feet long. 660 times eight equals, you guessed it, 5,280 ft.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This continued until a major change took place around 200 years ago. As the Age of Discovery came to an end and industry grew primarily in Western Europe, it became necessary to unify units of length on a global scale. In the 17th century, discussions were held in Europe regarding the unification of units. After a century of discussions, France proposed the unit of the meter (meaning "to measure" in Greek) in 1791. The reference at this time was the distance of the meridian from the north pole to the equator. One meter was set as 1/10,000,000 of this distance. Today, one meter is defined as "the distance that light travels in a vacuum in 1/299,792,458 of a second," as defined in 1983.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For navigation on water (marine), air, and space the nautical mile unit of length is used. Historically, a nautical mile was defined as the meridian arc length corresponding to one minute of a degree of latitude. Nautical mile is based on Earth’s circumference being 360 degrees. These degrees can then be divided into 60 minutes. One of these minutes (or minutes of arc as they are called in navigation) along a great circle on Earth represents one nautical mile. Today the international nautical mile is defined as exactly 1,852 meters (6,076 ft; 1.151 mi).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In terms of statute or land miles, a nautical mile represents 1.15 miles. This is because one degree of latitude is approximately 69 statute miles in length. 1/60th of that measure would be 1.15 statute miles. </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection" xml:id="engineering-measurement-length-units">
            <Title>Length Units</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In the US standard system, the inch (in) 1” (double apostrophe) is the primary unit, with the foot (ft) 1’ (single apostrophe) and mile (mi) used for larger distances.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In the metric system, the base unit for length is the meter (m). Its subdivisions include the centimeter (cm), millimeter (mm). The kilometer (km), equivalent to 1,000 m is used for longer distances.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For navigation on water (marine), air, and space, the <term>Nautical Mile</term> (NM) unit of length is used.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <table>
                  <title> Length units for US Standard and Metric systems</title>
                  <tabular>
                     <row header="yes">
                        <cell>U.S. Standard</cell>
                        <cell>Metric</cell>
                        <cell>Conversions</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12 inches = 1 foot</cell>
                        <cell>1 centimeter (cm) = 10 millimeters</cell>
                        <cell> 1 inch = 2.54 cm</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 feet = 1 yard</cell>
                        <cell>1 meter = 100 centimeters</cell>
                        <cell>1 ft = 0.3048 m</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1,760 yards = 1 mile</cell>
                        <cell>1 kilometer = 100,000 centimeters</cell>
                        <cell>1 yd = 0.9144 m</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5,280 feet = 1 mile</cell>
                        <cell> 1 kilometer = 1,000 meters</cell>
                        <cell> 1 mile = 1.6093 km</cell>
                     </row>
                  </tabular>
               </table>
            </item>
            <item>
               <table>
                  <title> Length units for US Standard and Metric systems</title>
                  <tabular>
                     <row>
                        <cell> 1 Nautical Mile = 6,076 ft</cell>
                        <cell>1 Standard Mile = 5,280 ft</cell>
                        <cell>1 Kilometer = 3,280.84 ft</cell>
                     </row>
                  </tabular>
               </table>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="length_comparison"><!-- Source:  roger gill/>
  -->
                  <caption>Visual comparison of Kilometer, Statute Mile and Nautical mile</caption>
                  <image width="60%" source="images/length_comparison.png"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Fathom: A nautical measurement equal to 6 feet or 1.8288 meters. It is commonly used for measuring depth in water. Finger tip to finger tip </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure>
                  <caption>Fathom</caption>
                  <image width="40%" source="images/fathom.png"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection"
                 xml:id="engineering-measurement-length-measuring-instruments">
            <Title>Length Measuring Instruments</Title>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Rulers and Yardsticks</term> are straight, flat measuring tools commonly used for shorter lengths. A ruler measure 1 ft. or 12 inches whereas a yardstick measure 3 ft. or 1 yd.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/ruler.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/yardstick.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>Tape Measure</term> is a flexible tape marked with inches and feet for measuring longer distances. It is often used in construction and carpentry. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/tapemeasure.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Calipers or callipers are used to measure he dimensions of an object, generally by placing two movable points of the instrument across the object or span to be measured..</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/calipers.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>micrometer</term>, sometimes known as a <term>micrometer screw gauge</term>, is a device incorporating a calibrated screw widely used for accurate measurement of components. Outside, inside, and depth micrometers are all used. The outside micrometer has a unit conversion chart between fractional and decimal inch measurements etched onto the frame</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/micrometer.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>surveyor's tape</term> is a long, flexible tape marked in meters used in land surveying.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>sextant</term> is a navigation instrument used to measure the angle between celestial objects and the horizon. It helps determine a ship's position at sea. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/sextant.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Microwave instruments</term> use microwaves to take survey measurements. They have a range up to 100 km and are comprised of two identical units, a master unit, and a remote unit.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Infrared wave instruments </term>use amplitude modulated infrared waves and prism reflectors. They have a range up to 3 km and accuracy of +/- 10mm.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Light wave instruments</term> rely on the propagation of modulated light waves. Their accuracy varies from 0.5mm to 5mm/km, and they have a daytime range of 3km and night range of 2.5km.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Laser measuring tools</term> send a beam to the target, which reflects off the surface and is sent back to the device. Lasers are focused beams of light that stay at a particular frequency. And because they travel from one place to another at a fairly constant rate, they can be used to measure distance with a great deal of accuracy. A laser measuring device also has a longer range than many other measuring tools, which gives it an advantage over other devices that become less precise the farther out you measure. Lasers are less likely to disperse than white light, so they can travel at a greater distance without losing their intensity. They keep most of their intensity once they reflect off a target, which is important if you want to get accurate distance measurements.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/laser.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Sonar</term> is an object-finding system that uses sound waves to determine the distance, speed of and direction to objects within its range. ..</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <image width="50%" source="images/sonar.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>These instruments allow engineers, sailors, and others to accurately measure lengths and distances according to their respective systems of measurement. It's important to note that many professionals now use digital instruments, such as laser distance measurers, which can provide precise measurements in multiple units.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection" xml:id="engineering-measurement-unit-conversions">
            <Title>Unit Conversions</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Frequently, engineers need to find length equivalents between different systems of measurement. For example, in the construction of a ship there may be different contractors, some of whom use US standard measurement and others who use metric. Since the agreed upon system is metric, conversions are required to standardize all measurements.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Conversion of units</term> is the process to convert between different units of measurement for the same quantity, typically through multiplicative <term>conversion factors</term> which change the measured quantity value without changing its effects. Unit conversion is often easier within the metric or the SI than in others, due to the regular 10-base in all units and the prefixes that increase or decrease by 3 powers of 10 at a time.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The <term>unit-factor method</term> or the <term>unity bracket method</term> is a widely used technique for unit conversions using the rules of algebra. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The<term> factor-label method</term> is the sequential application of conversion factors expressed as fractions and arranged so that any dimensional unit appearing in both the numerator and denominator of any of the fractions can be cancelled out until only the desired set of dimensional units is obtained. For example, 10 miles per hour (mi/hr or mph) can be converted to meters per second (m/s) by using a sequence of conversion factors as shown below:</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection" xml:id="engineering-measurement-example">
            <Title>Example</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Using unit-factor method we can express a distance in meters from feet as:</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>To Find distance in meters = (distance in ft) <m>\times</m> (12 in/1 ft) <m>\times</m> (2.54 cm/1 in) <m>\times </m>(1 m/100 cm)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The Conversion factor is .3048 m/ft</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>distance in meters = (distance in ft) x 0.3048 m/ft</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 foot = 12”/1 ft <m>\times</m> 2.54 cm/1” = 30.48 cm/ft</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 foot = 1 M/100 cm <m>\times</m> 30.48 cm = 0.3048 Meters </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Conversion Factor = .3048</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 meter =1ft/12 in <m>\times</m> 1 in/2.54 cm <m>\times</m> 100 cm/1 m=100 /30.48</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 meter = 100/30 =3.28 ft</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Conversion Factor</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 foot = 0.3048 m</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 inch = 2.54 cm</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Nautical Miles</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 Statute Mile= 1 Statute Mile/5280 ft x 6076 ft/1 NM = 1.15 Mile/NM</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Conversion Factor = 1.15 mile/NM</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>1 km =1.852 NM</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection" xml:id="engineering-measurement-example-problem">
            <Title>Example Problem</Title>
            <item>
               <p>The last example explains how to convert meters to inches. We start with the same units as in the first example, but finish with different units. There will be two separate conversions. First, we convert from meters to feet. Then we convert from feet to inches. Remember, there are </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Convert </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Feet to Meters</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Meters to Feet</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Miles to KM</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>KM to Miles</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>7 meters to inches.&#x2028;7 meters × 3.28084 feet</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>&#x2028;</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Temperature</Title>
         <item>
            <p> Temperature is a measure of the average kinetic energy of the particles in a substance. It quantifies how hot or cold an object or environment is relative to a standard or reference point. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The most commonly used temperature scale in the US today is the Fahrenheit scale, abbreviated F. In this scale, water freezes at 32 degrees and boils at 212 degrees. (This only holds strictly when atmospheric pressure equals the average sea level pressure. At high altitudes, water boils at a lower temperature, as anyone who cooks in the mountains knows.) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Another common scale is the Celsius (also called Centigrade) scale. In this scale, water freezes at 0 degrees and boils at 100 degrees. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are also temperature scales in which zero is absolute zero, the lowest possible temperature. (People have gotten close to absolute zero, but have never reached it. According to theory, we never will.) Absolute zero is at -273.15 Celsius, or -459.67 Fahrenheit. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Kelvin temperature scale uses the same size degree as Celsius, but has its zero set to absolute zero. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Rankine temperature scale uses the same size degree as Fahrenheit, but has its zero set to absolute zero </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Celsius and Kelvin scales are part of the International System of Units (SI), providing a standardized and widely adopted system for expressing temperatures. Celsius is the more common scale for everyday use, while Kelvin is often used in scientific and thermodynamic calculations. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Temperature Scales</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/temperature-scales.jpeg"/>
               <!--https://i.pinimg.com/564x/69/c4/40/69c440d7157ddf822874beb7c9adef63.jpg-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To convert between Fahrenheit and Celsius use these formulas: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Celsius to Fahrenheit</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">° F = 9/5 ( ° C) + 32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Kelvin to Fahrenheit</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">° F = 9/5 (K - 273) + 32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Fahrenheit to Celsius</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">° C = 5/9 (° F - 32)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Celsius to Kelvin</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">K = ° C + 273</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Kelvin to Celsius</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">° C = K - 273</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>Fahrenheit to Kelvin</em>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">K = 5/9 (° F - 32) + 273</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These formulas allow you to convert temperatures between different scales. It's important to use the appropriate formula based on the units provided or required for a specific calculation or conversion. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.6.2 Instruments Used to Measure Temperature </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Various instruments are used to measure temperature in different applications. The choice of temperature measurement instrument depends on factors such as the required accuracy, temperature range, and the specific application or industry. Different instruments are suitable for different temperature ranges and environments. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Here are some common instruments used to measure temperature: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermometers: are the most common instruments for measuring temperature. They come in various types, including mercury thermometers, alcohol thermometers, and digital thermometers. The basic principle involves the expansion or contraction of a temperature-sensitive substance in response to temperature changes. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Liquid in Glass Thermometer: This type of thermometer uses a liquid (usually mercury or colored alcohol) sealed in a glass tube. The liquid expands or contracts with temperature changes, and the temperature is read from a scale on the thermometer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Liquid in Glass Thermometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image1.png"/>
               <!--Picture 106-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bimetallic temperature sensors use the differential expansion of two metals to detect temperature changes. These are often used in thermostats and mechanical temperature gauges. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Bimetallic Temperature Sensor</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image2.png"/>
               <!--Bimetallic Thermometer | Tameson.com-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermocouple: a temperature sensor made from two different metals joined at one end. When exposed to temperature variations, it generates a small electrical voltage proportional to the temperature difference. It is widely used for temperature measurement in various engineering applications. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Thermocouple</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image3.png"/>
               <!--Picture 107-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Resistance Temperature Detector: RTD is an acronym used for resistance temperature detector. It is a temperature sensor that allows determining the temperature by measuring the resistance of the electrical wire. This electrical wire acts as a temperature sensor. Basically, in this, there is a metallic wire present and with the increase in the amount of heat experienced by the metallic substance, there is a change (rise) in resistance due to variation in the hotness of the wire. However, the resistance of the wire falls when the amount of heat supplied to the wire decreases. In this way, the change in resistance of the wire either increase or decrease signifies the temperature change and in this way variation in temperature through variation in resistance is predicted. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Resistance Temperature Device RTD</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image2.jpeg"/>
               <!--RTD temperature measurement | Endress+Hauser-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermistor: a type of temperature-sensitive resistor whose electrical resistance changes significantly with temperature. It is commonly used in electronic devices and temperature control systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Thermistor</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/thermister.png"/>
               <!--Thermistor Working Principle • Blaze Probes-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Infrared (IR) Thermometer: An IR thermometer measures temperature without direct contact with the object. It detects the infrared radiation emitted by the object, converting it into a temperature reading. IR thermometers are particularly useful for non-contact measurements or in hazardous environments. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Infrared Thermometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image3.jpeg"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Pressure</Title>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure is the measure of a perpendicular force exerted per unit area on the boundaries of a substance (or system). It is caused by the collisions of the molecules of the substance with the boundaries of the system. As molecules hit the walls, they exert forces that try to push the walls outward. The forces resulting from all of these collisions cause the pressure exerted by a system on its surroundings. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Pressure acting on a body</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/pressure-on-body.png"/>
               <!--Picture 1730183778-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure is directly proportional to force and inversely proportional to the area over which the force is applied. Increasing the force applied to a surface or decreasing the area increases the pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mathematically, pressure is expressed as: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure = <m>\frac{Force}{Area}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.7.2 PRESSURE SCALES </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure scales are systems used to measure and quantify pressure. There are several types of pressure scales, including: Atmospheric Pressure, Absolute Pressure, Gauge Pressure, Vacuum Pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric Pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Air, which is all around you, has weight, and it presses against everything it touches. This pressure is called atmospheric pressure, or air pressure. Atmospheric pressure is the force exerted on a surface by the air above it as gravity pulls it to Earth. Atmospheric pressure is the pressure exerted by the Earth's atmosphere at a given location. Elevation affects atmospheric pressure. For example, standard atmospheric pressure at sea level is approximately 14.7 psia or 101.325 kPa. In Denver, Colorado, atmospheric pressure is 12.4 psia or about 84.0 kPa, and in Death Valley, California it is 14.9 psia or 102.6 kPa. Atmospheric pressure is commonly measured with a barometer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Atmospheric Pressure</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image4.png"/>
               <!--8: Visual representation of air pressure within the atmosphere region | Download Scientific Diagram-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 atmosphere equals: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> in US customary units:14.7 psia at Sea Level </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> in International System of Units (SI) System:101.325 kPa at Sea Level </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> in gauge pressure, 0 gauge = One Atmosphere at Sea Level = 14.7 psia = 101.325 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Gauge Pressure</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image5.png"/>
               <!--Picture 93-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vacuum Pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure below atmospheric pressure is designated as a vacuum. A Vacuum gauge is used to measure vacuum pressure and is measured in inches mercury gauge (inHg). A perfect vacuum corresponds to absolute zero pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 0 gauge = One Atmosphere at Sea Level = 14.7 psia = 101.325 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 29.92 inHg gauge = 760 Torr = 0 inches Hg Absolute Scale </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Partial Vacuum gauge pressure measurements require conversions which will be discussed in the following sections. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Vacuum Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image4.jpeg"/>
               <!--Vacuum Gauge-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Pressure Scales </caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image6.png"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.7.3 UNITS FOR MEASURING PRESSURE AND CONVERSIONS </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are numerous units of measurement for pressure: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard Pressure, pounds per square inch (psi) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> International (SI) or Metric, pascal or kilo-pascal, Newtons per Meter Squared (kPa) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric Pressure (atm) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure (psia) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge Pressure (psig) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Head Pressure (feet) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torr (torr) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bar (Bar) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge Vacuum (inHg) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Compound Gauge (psig and inHg) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dual Gauge (Multiple Units) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Guage for Inches of water (in H20) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Units </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are two basic systems utilized today for measurement, the US Standard and the SI, or International System. The unit of measurement used depends upon what System(s) are involved, and therefore Conversion factors are used to go between systems. We have seen this in the chapter sections on length, area, volume, and time. In terms of measuring pressure, the US System uses psi or pounds per square inch. The International System uses newtons per centimeter squared, or kilopascals (kPa). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard System (psi) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the US standard system, pressure is commonly measured using pounds per square inch (psi) in which the force units are pounds (lbs.) and the area units are square inches <em>(</em>
               <m>{in.}^{2}</m>). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The psi unit represents the amount of force (in pounds) exerted on a one-square-inch area. For instance, a pressure of 30 psi means that a force of 30 pounds is distributed over each square inch of the surface. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure = <m>\frac{Force}{Area}</m> =<m>\frac{Pounds}{InchesSquared}</m> =<m>\frac{lbs.}{{in.}^{2}}</m> = psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure =<m>\frac{Force}{Area}</m> =<m>\frac{Force = ma}{Area}</m> F = ma (mass x acceleration) = <m>\frac{mx{32.2fts}^{2}}{Area}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> International System of Units (SI)/Metric (kPa) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the metric system, pressure is typically measured using kilopascals (kPa), which represent newtons per square meter (N/m²). One pascal is equal to one newton of force distributed over a one-square-meter area. However, this is a relatively small pressure, so in practical applications, kilopascals (kPa) or megapascals (MPa) are commonly used. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One newton is the force needed to accelerate one kilogram of mass at the rate of one meter per second squared. So, we can say one newton is one kgm/s². </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Force Units are measured in pascals or kilopascals (newtons). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Area Units are measured in centimeters or meters squared. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the SI system, pressure is described in pascals (Pa). Since Pressure = Force/Area, the equation for measuring pressure in pascals is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure (pascals) = <m>\frac{Force}{Area}</m> =<m>\frac{Newtons}{MetersSquared}</m> =<m>\frac{N}{m^{2}}</m> = <m>\frac{kg}{mxs^{2}}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure = <m>\frac{Force}{Area}</m>
               <m>\frac{Newtons}{Meterssquared}</m>= <m>\frac{F = ma}{MetersSquared}</m> = <m>\frac{kgxM/s^{2}}{MetersSquared}</m>=<m>\frac{Forceduetogravity = 9.8m/s^{2}}{Area}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric Pressure (psia) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric pressure, as stated earlier, is specific to elevation. Air, which is all around you, has weight, and it presses against everything it touches. That pressure is called atmospheric pressure, or air pressure. It is the force exerted on a surface by the air above it as gravity pulls it to Earth. Atmospheric pressure is the pressure exerted by the Earth's atmosphere at a given location. For example, standard atmospheric pressure at sea level is 760mmHg, 14.7 psia or 101.325 kPa. In Denver, Colorado, atmospheric pressure 12.4 psi or about 84.0 kPa, and in Death Valley, California it is 14.9 psi or 102.6 kPa. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric pressure is commonly measured with a barometer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Atmosphere at Sea Level = 14.7 psi, 101.325 kPa and 760 mmHg (1 Torr). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure (psia) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute pressure is the numerical scale that starts at zero, where zero corresponds to the vacuum of space. Absolute value is elevation dependent, meaning absolute pressure increases the closer one gets to Earth, and continues to increase the further one travels towards Earth’s center. For example, absolute pressure at sea level is 14.7 psia. In Death Valley, which is below sea level, absolute pressure is 14.9 psia. The densities of different liquids will also affect absolute pressure, so the deeper an object is placed in fluid, the more pressure it will experience. Absolute pressure is always greater than the corresponding gauge pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For shipboard purposes if you are utilizing a gauge, you can simply add 14.7 psi to the gauge reading in psi to get the absolute pressure. For example, a gauge pressure of 100 psig would be the same as an absolute pressure of 114.7 psia. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge pressure (psig) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Since the absolute atmospheric pressure is always present, and acts on everything equally, we normally don’ even notice it. Pressures are usually measured up or down from atmospheric pressure, and an ordinary pressure gauge reads zero when it is subjected to atmospheric pressure only. Pressures measured in this way are called gauge pressure. It is important to distinguish between gauge pressure and the absolute pressure described in the next section. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge pressures start at zero and increase with positive values with the range dependent on what system application is being measured. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vacuum Gages also start at zero and increase with negative values with the greatest value of vacuum being 29.92 inHg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> We sometimes say psig to indicate gauge pressure and other times we merely say psi. By common convention, gauge pressure is always assumed when pressure is given in pounds per square inch, pounds per square foot, or similar units. The “g” (for gauge) is added only when there is some possibility of confusion. Absolute pressure, on the other hand, is always expressed as pounds per square inch absolute (psia), and so forth. It is always necessary to establish clearly just what kind of pressure we are talking about, unless this is very clear from the nature of the discussion. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>P</em>
                        <m>gage</m> = <em>P</em>
                        <m>abs</m> − <em>P</em>
                        <m>atm</m>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">gauge pressure</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <m>P_{gagevac}</m>= <em>P</em>
                        <m>atm</m> − <em>P</em>
                        <m>abs</m>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">vacuum pressure</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>P</em>
                        <m>abs</m> = <em>P</em>
                        <m>atm</m> + <em>P</em>
                        <m>gage</m>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">absolute pressure</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> gauge equations </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge to Absolute Pressure Conversions </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge to absolute Pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Psig = psia - patm<!-- linebreak --><!-- linebreak -->US Customary System<!-- linebreak -->For shipboard purposes, you can simply add 14.7 psi to the gage reading in psi to get the absolute pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge Pressure = 0 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric Pressure = 14.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure = 14.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gage Pressure = 100 psig </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atmospheric Pressure = 14.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure = <em>P</em>
               <m>abs</m> = <em>P</em>
               <m>atm</m> + <em>P</em>
               <m>gage</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure = 14.7 psia + 100 psig </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Absolute Pressure = 114.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> SI System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gage Pressure = 0 kPa = Atmospheric Pressure = 101.325 kPa =14.7psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Atmosphere =<m>\frac{USSystem}{MetricSystem}</m> = <m>\frac{14.7psia}{101.325kPa}</m> = .145 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Or </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Atmosphere= <m>\frac{MetricSystem}{USSystem}</m> = <m>\frac{101.325kPa}{14.7psia}</m> = 6.89 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example Problems: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Convert 122 kPa to psi. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Dual Gauge: kPa and psi</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image5.jpeg"/>
               <!--C:\Users\rgill.MARITIME-EDU\AppData\Local\Microsoft\Windows\INetCache\Content.MSO\8DE55C2C.tmp-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 122kPa x <m>\frac{14.7psia}{101.325kPa}</m> = 17.7 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Convert 35 psig to kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 35 psig + 14.7 psia = 49.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 49.7 psia x <m>\frac{101.325kPa}{14.7psia}</m> = 343 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Head Pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Head pressure pertains to the pressure exerted by a fluid due to the weight of the fluid a vertical distance above a certain reference point. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> It is commonly measured in meters (m) or feet (ft). Essentially, head pressure represents the potential energy that a fluid possesses, which can be converted into work or kinetic energy. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A vertical column of water 2.31 feet high exerts one pound of force over one square inch. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> When measuring head pressure, the specific gravity of a fluid must be included. Specific gravity is a measure of the density of a substance in comparison to the density of water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Specific Gravity of fresh water equals 1. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure/Head Conversion Formula </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>The weight of one cubic foot of fresh water is of 62.427 pounds.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image7.png"/>
               <!--Picture 2-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>The weight of one cubic foot of fresh water is of 62.427 pounds.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image6.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 4-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water one foot high distributed over one square inch = .433 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> What this relationship is saying is that for every foot we go up in height, we add 0.433 pounds per square inch at the base of an object. Or we multiply the height of the water by 0.433. Keep in mind that we are talking about water here and specifically the density and weight of water. Other liquids will have their own density, and therefore the psi at the bottom of a column of another liquid would be different than that of water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example problems: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water 10 ft high exerts what pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer___________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Column of water 100 ft high exerts what pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer___________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Column of water one foot high</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image8.png"/>
               <!--Picture 456013673-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For columns of water less than one foot, we multiply the height in inches by .036 psi. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are 12 inches in 1 foot, therefore <m>\frac{.433psiperfoot}{12inchesperfoot}</m> = .036 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Inch of Water = .036 psi. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water 12 inches high exerts what pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer____________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water 6 inches high exerts what pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer___________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>One Cubic Inch of Fresh Water</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image9.png"/>
               <!--Cubic inches-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water 2.31 feet in height gives us a pressure at the base of 1 psi. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <m>\frac{1poundofwaterequalswhatverticaldistance?}{1footofwaterexerts.433psi}</m> = <m>\frac{1psiwater}{.433\frac{psi}{foot}/water}</m> =<m>\frac{1psi}{.433psi}</m> = 2.31 feet of water exerts one pound force </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A column of water 4.62 ft exerts what pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer_________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> How high a column of water exerts 5lbs pressure? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer___________________ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Column of Water 2.31 feet in height exerting 1psi. illustration.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image10.png"/>
               <!--Picture 3-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Instruments Used to Measure Pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure can be measured directly by measurement of the applied force. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Before mechanical manometers and electronic diaphragm pressure sensors were invented, pressure was measured by liquid manometers with mercury or water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mercury (abbreviated Hg) heavier liquid metal </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Fresh Water (abbreviated H20) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mercury </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mercury is a useful material to use in a manometer because of its high density. This means that a much shorter column is needed compared to water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mercury is commonly used in barometers because its high density means the height of the column can be a reasonable size to measure atmospheric pressure. A barometer using water, for instance, would need to be 13.6 times taller than a mercury barometer to obtain the same pressure difference. This is because mercury is 13.6 times denser than water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 inch of mercury = .491 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 pound of mercury = 2.036 inches </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 inch of mercury = 13.6 inches of water </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 inch of water =.0736 inches of mercury </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A manometer is a simple instrument used to measure pressure differences in a fluid. It typically involves a column of liquid, and the pressure difference causes a change in the liquid's height, which can be measured to determine the pressure, dependent upon the liquid’s density. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A U-tube manometer is probably the most common manometer in use today. These devices typically use a column of liquid to indicate the pressure difference between two points. Pressure is read on a scale as the difference in height (h) between the two liquid columns. The units of measure commonly used are inches of water and inches of mercury. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Measuring pressure </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In a U-tube manometer the tube is filled until both sides are approximately half full. When the pressures are equal, the column of liquid on each side will be at the same height. This is usually marked as zero on a scale. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> With both sides of the manometer open to the atmosphere, the fluid level on one side will be the same as the level on the other side because P1 equals P2. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>U-tube manometer </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Now suppose one end of the U-tube manometer is connected to an unknown pressure P1 whose value must be determined. The other end is left exposed to the atmospheric pressure, P2. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The difference in the height of the liquid on the two sides of the tube is the differential pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>U-tube manometer utilizing water</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image11.png"/>
               <!--Measuring differential pressure.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The total difference in liquid height is 4 units, which means that our pressure differential is 4 inches of water column. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Figure 1. With both ends of the tube open, the liquid is at the same height in each leg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Figure 2. When positive pressure is applied to one leg, the liquid is forced down in that leg and up in the other. The difference in height, “h,” which is the sum of the readings above and below zero, indicates pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Figure 3. When a vacuum is applied to one leg, the liquid rises in that leg and falls in the other. The difference in height, “h,” which is the sum of the readings above and below zero, indicates the amount of the vacuum. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Manometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image12.png"/>
               <!--Picture 86-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Types of fluids </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> As we said earlier, a manometer is filled with a liquid. Typical manometer liquids are mercury, water, and light oils. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> It’s worth saying here that mercury was a common manometer fluid in the past, but has largely been replaced due to its environmental and health hazards. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Quite often the liquid is colored to help detect the fluid movement. Here, the specific gravity of the manometer fluids must be included to convert Head to pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure =<m>\frac{HeadXS.G}{2.31}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Liquids of Different Densities</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image13.png"/>
               <!--Manometer Fluids-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> TORR </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 atmosphere of pressure at sea level is equal to 760 torr. The torr is named after the Italian physicist Evangelista Torricelli (<em>1608 – 1647</em>), who invented the mercury barometer. When Torricelli first used mercury to measure atmospheric pressure, he found that the pressure supported a column of mercury about 760 millimeters high and 1 torr being 1 mm in height of Hg. 760 mmHg is equivalent to 29.92 inches. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Mercury Barometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image14.png"/>
               <!--Picture 97-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 atm = 14.7 psia, 101.325 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1atm =760 mmHg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 760 torr = 101.325 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 760 torr = 14.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 29.92 in hg =14.7psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example Problem </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Meteorologists state that a “falling” barometer indicates an approaching storm. Given a barometric pressure of 27.5 in. Hg, express the pressure in each of the following units of pressure: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> a. Atmospheres </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> b. mmHg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> c. kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> d. psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solution </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For each conversion, we apply a unit conversion factor related to units of standard pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> (a) To express the pressure in atmospheres, we derive a unit factor related to the equivalent relationship, 29.9 inHg = 1 atm. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 27.5 inHg X <m>\frac{1atm}{29.92inHg}</m> = 0.9 atm </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> (b) To convert to millimeters of mercury, we derive a unit factor related to the equivalent relationship, 29.9 inHg = 760 mmHg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 27.5 inHg x <m>\frac{760mmHg}{29.92inHg}</m>= 699 mmHg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> (c) To find the pressure in kilopascals, we derive a unit factor related to the equivalent relationship </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 29.9 inHg = 101.325 kPa. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 27.5 inHg X <m>\frac{101.325kPa}{29.92inHg}</m> = 93kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the pressure in pounds per square inch, we derive a unit factor related to the equivalent relationship, 29.9 inHg = 14.7 psi. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 27.5 inHg x <m>\frac{14.7psia}{29.92inHg}</m> = 13.5 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> BAR </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The bar is defined using the SI derived unit, pascal: 1 bar= =100,000 Pa (100 kPa). =100,000 N/m2. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 bar is slightly less than the current average atmospheric pressure on Earth at sea level being 14.5 psia. The bar and the millibar were introduced by the Norwegian meteorologist Vilhelm Bjerknes, who was a founder of the modern practice of weather forecasting. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Atmosphere =<m>\frac{USSystem}{MetricSystem}</m> = <m>\frac{14.7psia}{101.325kPa}</m> = .145 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar = 100 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 100 kPa X .145 = 14.5 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar =14.5 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>bar Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image15.png"/>
               <!--Picture 88-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar = 100,000 Pa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar = 14.5 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar = 750 torr </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Bar= 0.98 atm </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To convert 5 bars to psi, you use the conversion factor: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 bar = 14.5 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> So, for 5 bars: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 5 bars×14.5psi/bar = 73 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To convert 5 bars to kilopascals (kPa), you can use the conversion factor: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 bar = 100 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> So, for 5 bars: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 5 bars ×100 kPa/bar = 500kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge Vacuum (inHg) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bourdon Tube Vacuum Gauges are used to measure pressures less than atmospheric pressure with the Vacuum Gauge range from 0 to 30 inches Hg. Atmospheric pressure at Sea Level is 14.7 psia or 101.325 kPa, which corresponds to 0 gauge. When in use and the vacuum increasing, the needle will move towards larger numbers with 29.92 inHg being the greatest achievable vacuum at Sea Level, as per Torricelli’s experiment. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vacuum pressure gauges and Pressure gauges, both start at zero-gauge pressure with zero-gauge pressure corresponding to atmospheric pressure. When the vacuum pressure gauge decreases below atmospheric, the vacuum gauge needle will begin to move off zero and move towards 29.92 in Hg gauge, stopping at the reduced pressure being measured. The value of 29.92 inches of mercury (inHg) gauge corresponds to the maximum possible vacuum that can be achieved relative to the atmospheric pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 0 Gauge Pressure = Atmospheric Pressure, 14.7 psia in US Customary Units or 101.325 kPa in SI Units. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Almost all Vacuum Gauge readings will be somewhere between 0 and 29.92 inHg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In working with Inches Mercury Gauge readings, it is essential to convert those readings into psia (absolute) values. The converted readings can be used when consulting Steam Tables for additional properties related those readings. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Vacuum Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image4.jpeg"/>
               <!--Vacuum Gauge-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One Atmosphere at Sea Level </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 0 psi gauge </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 14.7 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 101.325 kPa </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 760 Torr </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Perfect vacuum </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 29.92 inHg vacuum, gauge, often rounded to 30 in </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 0 Torr </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 0 inHg Absolute Scale </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 0 PSIA Scale </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vacuum Gauge problem </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">
                        <em>P</em>
                        <m>vac</m> = <em>P</em>
                        <m>atm</m> − <em>P</em>
                        <m>abs</m>
                     </cell>
                     <cell halign="left">vacuum pressure</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Let’s say the Vacuum Gauge indicates 10 inHg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> This indicates the pressure is <em>less than</em> atmospheric pressure and mercury is the measuring element. This reading, in Inches Mercury (inHg), must be converted to PSIA to utilize Steam Tables that are established on PSIA. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knowing One Inch of Mercury exerts .491 psi Hg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 10 inHg gauge can be multiplied by .491 psi Hg equaling 4.91 psi </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knowing 14.7 psia is Atmospheric Pressure and that inHg vacuum gauges indicate less than atmospheric: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vacuum Gauge Reading Equivalent psia = 14.7 psia – (10 inHg x .491 psi Hg) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 14.7 psia – (4.91 psi) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> = 9.79 psia </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Compound Gauge </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Measures pressure above and below atmospheric pressure. Zero is equal to atmospheric pressure with PSIG used above atmospheric pressure and inHg gauge used below atmospheric pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Compound Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image16.png"/>
               <!--Picture 90-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dual Scale Gage </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Dial contains a basic pressure scale and one or more additional concentric scales in equivalent values of a different pressure unit. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Dual Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image5.jpeg"/>
               <!--C:\Users\rgill.MARITIME-EDU\AppData\Local\Microsoft\Windows\INetCache\Content.MSO\8DE55C2C.tmp-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gauge; Inches of Water </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The units are conventionally used for measurement of certain pressure differentials such as small pressure differences across an orifice. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Inches of water Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image7.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 87-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.74 Pressure Gauge Construction </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A pressure gauge is a common instrument used to measure pressure in a wide range of applications. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bourdon Tube </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A bourdon pressure gauge is the most common type of pressure gauge and it uses a curved tube that straightens under pressure and shows the reading on a dial. The Bourdon gauge consists of a tube bent into a coil or an arc. As the pressure in the tube increases, the coil unwinds. A pointer connected to the end of the tube can be attached to a lever and a pointer calibrated to indicate pressure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Bourdon Tube Pressure Gauge</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image8.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 96-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure Transducer </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A pressure transducer is an electronic device that converts pressure into an electrical signal. It is often used in automated systems or where electronic data acquisition is required. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Pressure Transducer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image17.png"/>
               <!--Picture 85-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pressure is defined as force per unit area. Can pressure be increased in a fluid by pushing directly on the fluid? Yes, but it is much easier if the fluid is enclosed. The heart, for example, increases blood pressure by pushing directly on the blood in an enclosed system (valves closed in a chamber). If you try to push on a fluid in an open system, such as a river, the fluid flows away. An enclosed fluid cannot flow away, and so pressure is more easily increased by an applied force. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> What happens to a pressure in an enclosed fluid? Since atoms in a fluid are free to move about, they transmit the pressure to all parts of the fluid and to the walls of the container. Remarkably, the pressure is transmitted <em>undiminished</em>. This phenomenon is called Pascal’s principle, because it was first clearly stated by the French philosopher and scientist Blaise Pascal (1623–1662): A change in pressure applied to an enclosed fluid is transmitted undiminished to all portions of the fluid and to the walls of its container. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> PASCAL’S PRINCIPLE </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A change in pressure applied to an enclosed fluid is transmitted undiminished to all portions of the fluid and to the walls of its container. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pascal’s principle, an experimentally verified fact, is what makes pressure so important in fluids. Since a change in pressure is transmitted undiminished in an enclosed fluid, we often know more about pressure than other physical quantities in fluids. Moreover, Pascal’s principle implies that <em>the total pressure in a fluid is the sum of the pressures from different sources</em>. We shall find this fact—that pressures add—very useful. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Blaise Pascal had an interesting life in that he was home-schooled by his father who removed all of the mathematics textbooks from his house and forbade him to study mathematics until the age of 15. This, of course, raised the boy’s curiosity, and by the age of 12, he started to teach himself geometry. Despite this early deprivation, Pascal went on to make major contributions in the mathematical fields of probability theory, number theory, and geometry. He is also well known for being the inventor of the first mechanical digital calculator, in addition to his contributions in the field of fluid statics. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Application of Pascal’s Principle </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One of the most important technological applications of Pascal’s principle is found in a <em>hydraulic system</em>, which is an enclosed fluid system used to exert forces. The most common hydraulic systems are those that operate car brakes. Let us first consider the simple hydraulic system shown in <xref ref="one-cubic-inch"/>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="one-cubic-inch">
               <caption>1 cubic inch</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image9.jpeg"/>
               <!--A small force can be converted into a larger force when pressure is transmitted through liquids in different containers with pistons that are connected.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A typical hydraulic system with two fluid-filled cylinders, capped with pistons and connected by a tube called a hydraulic line. A downward force F1F1 on the left piston creates a pressure that is transmitted undiminished to all parts of the enclosed fluid. This results in an upward force F2F2 on the right piston that is larger than F1F1 because the right piston has a larger area. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Mass</Title>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is a fundamental property of matter that quantifies the amount of substance within an object. It is a measure of an object's resistance to acceleration when a force is applied, and it also determines the strength of its gravitational attraction to other objects. In physics, mass is typically measured in kilograms (kg) in the International System of Units (SI), or Pounds (lbs.) in the US Customary system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The greater the mass of an object, the more force is required to accelerate or decelerate it. Mass is an intrinsic property and is independent of an object's location in space. In engineering, mass plays a crucial role in calculations related to forces, motion, energy, and structural integrity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Key points about mass include: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Inertia: Mass is directly related to inertia, which is an object's resistance to changes in its state of motion. The greater the mass, the greater the force needed to accelerate or decelerate the object. An object with a larger mass would require a greater force to accelerate it and change its inertia than an object with a smaller mass. Therefore, an object's inertial mass definition is its resistance to changes in acceleration. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gravitational Interaction: Mass also determines the gravitational force between objects. According to Newton's law of universal gravitation, the force of attraction between two masses is directly proportional to the product of their masses and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between them. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Invariance: Mass is invariant, meaning it does not change regardless of the object's location or the reference frame from which it is measured. This is in contrast to weight, which can vary depending on the gravitational field strength. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Relativity: In the theory of relativity, mass is also related to energy. According to Einstein's famous equation E=mc2E = mc^2E=mc2, mass can be converted into energy and vice versa. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Conservation of Mass: The principle of the conservation of mass states that in a closed system, the total mass remains constant over time, regardless of the processes occurring within the system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In summary, mass is a measure of the quantity of matter in an object, contributing to both its inertia and its gravitational interaction with other objects. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.2.2 UNITS FOR MEASURING MASS </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pound (lb.): The pound is the most commonly used unit for everyday measurements of mass in the United States. One pound is equivalent to 16 ounces. One pound is equivalent to approximately 0.453592 kilograms. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Ounce (oz): The ounce is a smaller unit of mass often used for finer measurements. There are 16 ounces in a pound. One ounce is approximately 28.3495 grams. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To convert units from pounds to ounces, the number of pounds is multiplied by 16. Likewise, to convert from ounces to pounds, the mass value is divided by 16. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US TABLE 6.2.1 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 ounce=16 drams</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 pound=16 ounces</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 hundredweight (short)=100 pounds</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 hundredweight (long)=112 pounds</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 ton (short)= 2,000 pounds</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 ton (long)= 2,240 pounds</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The SI (International System of Units) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The mass unit that is typically used in SI is the kilogram (kg). However, the kilogram is easily converted to the gram (g) when multiplied by 1,000. Similarly, the gram (g) can be converted to milligrams (mg) by multiplying by 1,000. Conversely, milligrams are converted to grams by dividing by 1,000. Similarly, grams are converted to kilograms by dividing by 1,000. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gram (g): The gram is a smaller unit of mass frequently used for lighter objects or more precise measurements. One kilogram is equivalent to 1,000 grams. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Milligram (mg): The milligram is an even smaller unit used for very small masses, often in scientific and medical contexts. One gram is equivalent to 1,000 milligrams. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Microgram (µg): The microgram is an even smaller unit used for extremely small masses, especially in fields like chemistry and pharmacology. One microgram is equivalent to 0.001 milligrams. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These units are part of the International System of Units (SI) and provide a standardized way to express measurements of mass. The kilogram is especially important, as it is used as the base unit from which other metric units of mass are derived. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Metric Mass </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Milligram(mg)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> gram or 1/1000 gram </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Centigram(cg)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> gram or 1/100 gram </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Decigram (dg)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> gram or 1/10 gram </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Gram(g)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">1,000 milligrams</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Dekagram (dag)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">10 grams</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Hectogram (hg)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">100 grams</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Kilogram (kg)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">1,000 grams</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Metric ton(t)</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">1,000 kilograms</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">1 Kilogram</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">2.2 pounds</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Conversions </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> It is possible to convert a mass that is measured in US units to metric units and vice versa. One pound is equivalent to 453.6 grams. Thus, to convert a mass from pounds to the SI unit of kilograms, the number of pounds measured is multiplied by 453.6 grams, or 0.4536 kilograms, to determine the mass in grams. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Using this method, one English pound is equivalent to 0.4536 kilograms. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Conversion examples: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 Kilogram = 2.2 pounds </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Converting pounds to kilograms </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1-pound X <m>\frac{1kilogram}{2.2pounds}</m> = .45 kilograms </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Converting kilograms to grams </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 0.45 kilograms x <m>\frac{1,000grams}{1kilogram}</m> = 450 grams </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Converting kilograms to pounds </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1-kilogram x <m>\frac{2.2pounds}{1kilogram}</m> = 2.2 pounds </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 2-kilograms = how many pounds? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 2 kilograms x<m>\frac{2.2pounds}{1kilogram}</m> = 4.4 pounds </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.2.3 INSTRUMENTS FOR MEASURING MASS </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is measured by determining the extent to which a particle or object resists a change in its direction or speed when a force is applied. Isaac Newton stated: A stationary mass remains stationary, and a mass in motion at a constant speed and in a constant direction maintains that state of motion, unless acted on by an outside force. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For a given applied force, large masses are accelerated to a small extent, and small masses are accelerated to a large extent. The mass of an object can be calculated if the force and the acceleration are known. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The following formula applies: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>F</em> = <em>ma </em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where <em>F</em> is the applied force in newtons, <em>m</em> is the mass of the object or particle in kilograms, and <em>a</em> is the resulting acceleration in meters per second squared. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is typically measured using a balance or a scale. A balance compares the mass of an unknown object to that of known masses, while a scale measures the gravitational force acting on an object. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image18.png"/>
               <!--Picture 123-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> How is Mass Different from Weight? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A common misconception is that mass and weight are the same. However, weight is a measure of force and is determined by the mass of an object and its acceleration from the force of gravity exerted on it. Therefore, the weight of an object changes depending on its location and the force of gravity. For example, a person weighs more on Earth compared to the Moon or Mars. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is not relative to the force of gravity; mass is universal. A person's mass will not change on different planets or moons. Because it isn't probable or efficient to count the individual particles of matter that make up an object, it is preferable to use a balance to measure mass. A balance compares the unknown mass of an object to predetermined masses. Additionally, it is possible to determine an object's mass without a balance by using other information about the object and a subsequent formula that describes that information. Many different formulas include mass as a variable. Therefore, knowing other information about an object makes it possible to calculate the object's mass. For example: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F= ma </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=𝐹/𝑎 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knowing an object's weight, acceleration, or the force exerted on the object allows for the accurate determination of an object's unknown mass. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The formula for calculating weight is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> W=mg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In this equation, W is the variable for weight, m is the variable for mass, and g is the variable for acceleration due to gravity. On Earth, g is approximately 9.8 m/s/s. Like the force equation, the weight equation can be manipulated algebraically to solve for mass. In this case, the mass equation is m=W/g. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Different mechanisms are used to measure mass and weight. Mass is measured using a balance, which requires pre-established values for grams or kilograms. Weight is measured using a scale. A scale determines the amount of force that gravity enacts on the mass of an object. A scale cannot measure mass, but mass can be calculated from a scale weight with the use of the weight equation: (W=mg). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A person who weighs 175 pounds on a scale, experiences a force of approximately 778.44 Newtons. It is known that Earth's gravity accelerates mass at 9.8 meters per second squared. Given these variables, the weight equation is rearranged so mass is equal to weight divided by the acceleration of Earth's gravity as follows. Here's how to solve for mass using the weight formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=𝑊𝑔 (𝑀𝑎𝑠𝑠=𝑊𝑒𝑖𝑔ℎ𝑡 x 𝐴𝑐𝑐𝑒𝑙𝑒𝑟𝑎𝑡𝑖𝑜𝑛 𝑑𝑢𝑒 𝑡𝑜 𝐺𝑟𝑎𝑣𝑖𝑡𝑦) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=778.44𝑁 x 9.8𝑚/𝑠2 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚≈79.43𝑘𝑔 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Therefore, a person who weighs 175 pounds on Earth, has a calculated mass of 79.43 kilograms. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is not the same thing as weight. Weight has meaning only when an object having a specific mass is placed in an acceleration field, such as the gravitational field of the earth. Weight can vary depending on the strength of the gravitational field. At the earth's surface, a kilogram mass weighs about 2.2 pounds, for example. But on Mars, the same kilogram mass would weigh only about 0.8 pounds, and on Jupiter it would weigh roughly 5.5 pounds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Weight vs. Mass</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image19.png"/>
               <!--Picture 124-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Physics Mass Equations </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The mass of an object can be determined without the use of a balance by using a formula that has mass as a variable. In physics, a common method for how to find mass is associated with Sir Isaac Newton's second law of motion. This law describes an object's inertia and states that net force (F), measured in Newtons (N) equals mass (m) multiplied by acceleration (a), i.e., F=ma. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The equation variables can be algebraically rearranged to solve for mass so that m=F/a. Thus, if the amount of force applied to an object and its rate of acceleration is known, the mass of the object can be calculated by dividing the force by the acceleration. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝐹=𝑚𝑎 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝐹/𝑎=𝑚 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass can also be calculated when the weight of an object is known. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> W=mg </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> How to Find Mass </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are several options available to solve for mass. Which mass equation to use will depend on the situation and the available information. Consider the following examples using the physics mass equations. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example 1: Using Newton's Second Law of Motion (F=ma or m=F/a) to calculate mass. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A force of 150 N is applied to an object which then accelerates at 3 m/s/s. What is the mass of the object? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The example problem provides information about force and acceleration which means Newton's Second Law of Motion formula can be used (F=ma). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The formula must be rearranged algebraically to solve for mass (m). This is done by dividing both sides of the equation by acceleration (a): </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝐹=𝑚𝑎 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝐹/𝑎=𝑚𝑎/𝑎 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝐹/𝑎=𝑚 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Now the force (F) and acceleration (a) variables can be replaced by the values from the example problem: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 150𝑁/3𝑚/𝑠/𝑠=𝑚 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Finally, the value for force is divided by the value for acceleration to solve for mass: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 50𝑘𝑔=𝑚 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The object has a calculated mass of 50 kg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> When using Newton's Second Law to solve for mass, the equation shows mass to be a proportion of the force applied to an object to its acceleration. In this relationship, if the same force is applied to an object with a mass of 100 kg and to an object with a mass of 25 kg, the object with a mass of 25 kg will have a greater acceleration. This is because the object with a greater mass would require a greater applied force to achieve an acceleration equal to an object with a smaller mass. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example 2: Using weight and gravitational acceleration (W=mg or m=W/g) to calculate mass, </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> what is the mass of an object that weighs 150 pounds on Earth? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The example problem provides information about the weight of an object and its location, Earth, which has a gravitational acceleration of 9.8 m/s/s. This means the weight equation can be used. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The first step in this calculation is to convert the weight in pounds to its force in Newtons. This step can be done with an internet search or by multiplying the weight in pounds by 4.4482. Doing so provides a value of 667.2 N. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> With the weight (667.2 N) and gravitational acceleration (9.8 m/s/s) known, the values can replace the variables in the equation: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=𝑊/𝑔 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=667.2𝑁/9.8𝑚/𝑠/𝑠 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑚=68.1𝑘𝑔 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The object has a calculated mass of 68.1 kg. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The weight and gravitational acceleration equation is very similar to Newton's Second Law equation. Weight is a force and replaces the F variable from Newton's equation. Gravitational acceleration in the weight equation replaces the acceleration variable from Newton's Law and is a constant. On Earth, it is 9.8 m/s/s. Other planets and the moon have different values for gravitational acceleration. Thus, the more mass an object has, the greater the force of weight it will experience. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> What is mass equal to? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is equal to the following: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass is equal to the density multiplied by volume. Mass is equal to energy divided by the speed of light squared. Mass is equal to weight divided by the acceleration of gravity. Mass is also equal to net force divided acceleration. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> What is the formula for mass and weight? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The formula for weight states that weight is equal to mass multiplied by the acceleration of gravity (i.e., W=mg). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The formula for mass can therefore be m=W/g. However, mass is also equal to the net force needed to accelerate an object, divided by its acceleration (i.e., M = F/A). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> How is Mass Applied in Real Life? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knowing and understanding how the mass of an object affects its behavior has practical applications in a variety of fields that impact everyday life including astronomy, chemistry, and engineering. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For an astronomer, being able to determine the mass of a star provides information about how much and what type of elements it is burning for fuel along with its expected life span. Once the mass of a star is known, astronomers can use Einstein's energy equation to calculate the amount of energy produced by the star. According to experiments conducted by Albert Einstein, energy is equal to mass times the square of the speed of light. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Chemists must know the atomic mass or the mass of individual atoms to properly and safely mix chemical compounds to formulate products such as medications, household cleaning products, fertilizers, industrial solvents, and other products used regularly by people. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In all fields of engineering, an understanding of mass is essential, particularly as it is related to inertia and Newton's Second Law of Motion. An engineer tasked with constructing a skyscraper must understand and determine the necessary mass of the steel beams used in construction that will resist acceleration. Knowing and properly using this information will prevent the force of higher floors from crushing the lower floors of the building. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To summarize, mass is a fundamental property of matter, and its measurement is critical in engineering. In the United States customary system, mass is measured in pounds and ounces, while the metric system uses kilograms and grams. Conversion factors are used to convert between different units. By understanding mass and its measurement in both systems, engineering students can effectively apply these concepts in their studies and future careers. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Time</Title>
         <item>
            <p> Time is a fundamental and abstract concept that is used to order events, quantify the duration between events, and describe the progression of phenomena. It is one of the basic dimensions in the physical universe, along with length and mass. Time is considered a scalar quantity and is often measured in seconds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Below are several key concepts relating to time: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Temporal Order refers to the sequence or chronological arrangement of events or actions as they occur in time. It’s the concept that events happen in a specific order, one after another, according to the flow of time. Understanding temporal order is crucial in various fields such as storytelling, history, science, and everyday life, as it helps us make sense of cause-and-effect relationships and how events unfold over time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Relativity refers to the theory, proposed by Albert Einstein, wherein time is considered relative and can be experienced differently by observers moving at different speeds or in different gravitational fields. Time is often considered the fourth dimension in the context of spacetime, a concept that combines the three dimensions of space with the dimension of time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the fields of Physics and Mathematics time plays a crucial role in physics equations and mathematical models, describing the behavior of physical systems over time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Conservation of Energy is a fundamental principle of physics stating that the total energy of an isolated system remains constant over time. This means that energy can neither be created nor destroyed; it can only be transformed from one form to another (such as from kinetic energy to potential energy) or transferred between objects. Despite these changes, the total amount of energy within the system remains unchanged. This principle helps us understand and predict the behavior of physical systems over time, ensuring that energy calculations in any given situation will always balance out. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Circadian rhythm is the internal biological clock that regulates various physiological processes in living organisms, including sleep-wake cycles, hormone secretion, body temperature, and metabolism. These rhythms follow a roughly 24-hour cycle and are influenced by external cues like light and temperature. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In humans, the circadian rhythm is primarily controlled by the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) in the brain, which receives input from the eyes about light and darkness, helping to synchronize the internal clock with the external environment. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Disruptions to circadian rhythms, such as jet lag or shift work, can have significant effects on health and well-being, impacting sleep quality, mood, cognitive function, and overall physiological health. That's why maintaining a regular sleep schedule and exposure to natural light during the day are essential for keeping circadian rhythms in sync. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.3.2 Units of Time </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The standard units of time in the International System of Units (SI) are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Second (s): The second is the base unit of time in the SI system. It is defined as the duration of 9,192,631,770 periods of radiation corresponding to the transition between two hyperfine levels of the ground state of the cesium-133 atom. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Minute (min): One minute is equal to 60 seconds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Hour (h): One hour is equal to 60 minutes or 3,600 seconds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Day (d): One day is defined as 24 hours, or 86,400 seconds. It is based on the Earth's rotation period. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Week: A week consists of seven days. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Month: Months are somewhat arbitrary units of time that vary in length. The most common definitions are the calendar months, which have 28, 30, or 31 days. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Year (yr): A year is the time it takes for Earth to complete one orbit around the Sun. It is approximately 365.25 days. There are different types of years, such as the tropical year (based on the Earth's position relative to the Sun) and the sidereal year (based on the Earth's position relative to distant stars). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Decade: A decade is a period of ten years. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Century: A century is a period of one hundred years. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Millennium: A millennium is a period of one thousand years. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These units provide a way to express and measure various durations, from tiny fractions of a second to vast spans of time. Different fields and contexts may use specific units that are more relevant to their requirements; for example, astronomy may use units like light-years or parsecs to describe astronomical distances or cosmic timescales. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric time and Decimal time are two standards of measuring time. The decimal time uses decimal points to distinguish the units while the <em>metric system</em> does not. Some examples are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">Metric time</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">Decimal time</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">30 minutes</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">0.5 hours</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">45 minutes</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">0.75 hours</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Metric vs Decimal Time </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For units smaller than seconds, a prefix is used such as <em>milli</em>second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Many calendars even today use the sun, moon, and natural unit to keep time. As civilization and technology advanced, standard units and clocks made it easier for everyone to be able to identify and measure time. Time is now measured based on the vibrations of the cesium-133 atom. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Units of Time</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image20.png"/>
               <!--A table with numbers and a number of objects Description automatically generated with medium confidence-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Military Time </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Military time is a standardized timekeeping system used by the military, emergency services, and other organizations around the world. Rather than using a 12-hour standard clock with AM and PM designations, military time uses a <em>24-hour clock</em> system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In military time, each hour of the day is represented by a unique four-digit number. The first two digits represent the hour, and the second two digits represent the minutes. Therefore, 1600 military time is the way of expressing 4:00 PM in military format. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> This system is commonly used in military, aviation, emergency services, and other contexts where clarity and precision in timekeeping are critical. It eliminates confusion over AM and PM and simplifies calculations involving time intervals. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A watch system, watch schedule, or watch bill is a method of assigning regular periods of work duty aboard ships and some other areas of employment. A watch system allows the ship's crew to effectively operate the ship 24 hours a day for the duration of long voyages or operations. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Here's how military time corresponds to the traditional 12-hour clock: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 24-HOUR TIME CHART </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> (4 digits) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 0000 through 2359 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> NO <em>punctuation</em> and NO <em>a.m. or p.m. designation</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Midnight is the beginning of the new day. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 24 Hour Time </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> Standard Time </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 24 Hour Time </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> Standard Time </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0000 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 12:00 Midnight </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1200 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 12:00 Noon </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0030 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 12:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1230 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 12:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0100 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1300 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0130 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1330 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0200 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1400 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0230 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1430 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0300 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 3:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1500 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 3:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0330 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 3:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1530 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 3:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0400 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 4:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1600 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 4:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0430 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 4:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1630 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 4:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0500 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 5:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1700 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 5:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0530 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 5:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1730 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 5:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0600 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 6:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1800 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 6:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0630 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 6:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1830 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 6:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0700 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 7:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1900 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 7:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0730 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 7:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1930 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 7:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0800 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 8:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2000 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 8:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0830 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 8:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2030 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 8:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0900 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 9:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2100 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 9:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0930 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 9:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2130 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 9:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1000 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 10:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2200 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 0:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1030 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 10:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2230 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 10:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1100 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 11:00 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2300 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 11:00 PM </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left"> 1130 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 11:30 AM </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 2330 </cell>
                     <cell halign="left"> 11:30 PM </cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image21.png"/>
               <!--Picture 1-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> History of Time Measurement Units </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Time and its measurement study is called horology. Measuring of time started more than thirty thousand years ago. But back then, societies did not have clocks. Time was measured by the patterns of the moon, shadows of the sun, and the placement of the stars in the sky. These astronomical objects were widely used to determine time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Measuring time with celestial bodies has been a fundamental practice throughout human history. Early civilizations used the movements of celestial bodies like the Sun, Moon, and stars to track time, create calendars, and organize their daily activities. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solar time refers to the most basic form of time measurement, which is based on the apparent motion of the Sun across the sky. Ancient sundials, for example, relied on the position of the Sun's shadow to indicate the time of day. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Sundials - A sundial is a special structure created to determine the time of the day based on the shadow formed from the sun falling on it. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A lunar calendar is a calendar system based on the phases of the Moon. Unlike solar calendars, which are based on the Earth's orbit around the Sun, lunar calendars measure time by the Moon's cycles, typically from one new moon to the next. Each lunar month lasts about 29.5 days, resulting in a year of about 354 days, which is shorter than the 365 or 366 days in a solar year. Because of this difference, lunar calendars often require adjustments, such as the addition of an extra month, to stay in sync with the solar year. Lunar calendars are used in various cultures and religions for determining holidays, festivals, and other important dates. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Stars have also been important for timekeeping. The regular motion of certain stars across the night sky allowed navigators to determine their position and time of day, aiding in maritime navigation and long-distance travel. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Today, while we primarily rely on precise atomic clocks for accurate timekeeping, celestial bodies still play a role in time measurement, especially in fields like astronomy and navigation. For instance, astronomers use observations of distant celestial objects to coordinate universal time standards and to calibrate our atomic clocks. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The measurement of time has deep historical roots and is linked to the natural rhythms of the celestial bodies, especially the sun and the moon. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Humankind’s need to gauge the divisions of the day and night led the ancient Egyptians, Greeks, and Romans to create sundials, water clocks, and other early chronometric tools. Western Europeans adopted these technologies, but by the 13th century, demand for a dependable timekeeping instrument led medieval artisans to invent the mechanical clock. Although this new device satisfied the requirements of monastic and urban communities, it was too inaccurate and unreliable for scientific application until the pendulum was employed to govern its operation. The precision timekeepers that were subsequently developed resolved the critical problem of finding a ship's position at sea and went on to play key roles in the Industrial Revolution and the advance of Western civilization. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Celestial Time</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image22.png"/>
               <!--Picture 120-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.3.3 Instruments to Measure Time </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solar Day and Sundials: One of the earliest methods of measuring time is based on the solar day—the time it takes for the Earth to complete one rotation on its axis relative to the sun. Ancient cultures, such as the Egyptians and Babylonians, observed the motion of the sun's shadow to create sundials. These sundials divided the day into various parts based on the position of the sun. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Sundial</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image23.png"/>
               <!--Picture 119-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Timekeeping Devices: Instruments like clocks and watches are used to measure and quantify time intervals. These devices are based on various mechanisms, such as pendulums, gears, or electronic oscillators. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Today highly accurate timekeeping instruments set the beat for most of our electronic devices. Nearly all computers, for example, contain a quartz-crystal clock to regulate their operation. Moreover, not only do time signals beamed down from Global Positioning System satellites calibrate the functions of precision navigation equipment, but they do so as well for cellular telephones, instant stock-trading systems, and nationwide power-distribution grids. So integral have these time-based technologies become to our day-to-day lives that we recognize our dependency on them only when they fail to work. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Clocks, both analog and digital, are widely used to measure time. Analog clocks typically have hands that move around a circular dial, indicating hours, minutes, and sometimes seconds. Digital clocks display time using numerical digits. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Watches are portable timekeeping devices that individuals can wear on their wrists. They come in various styles, including analog, digital, and smartwatches, which offer additional functionalities beyond timekeeping. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Watches</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image10.jpeg"/>
               <!--21 Best Watches for Men in 2020 | GQ-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> An Hourglass consists of two glass bulbs connected by a narrow neck, with sand flowing through the neck. The time it takes for the sand to flow from one bulb to the other provides an estimate of a specific duration. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Hourglass</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image11.jpeg"/>
               <!--hourglass | meaning of hourglass in Longman Dictionary of Contemporary English | LDOCE-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Chronometer is a highly accurate timekeeping instrument, often used in navigation. Marine chronometers, for example, are designed to provide accurate timekeeping on ships. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Chronometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image12.jpeg"/>
               <!--FOUND: The Actual Marine Chronometer That Accompanied Charles Darwin at the HMS Beagle on his Journey to the Galapagos Islands - Monochrome Watches-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Atomic Clocks use the vibrations of atoms (usually cesium or rubidium) to measure time with extraordinary precision. These clocks form the basis for International Atomic Time (TAI) and Coordinated Universal Time (UTC). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Atomic Clock</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image13.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 118-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A stopwatch is a handheld timekeeping device used to measure elapsed time. It typically has buttons to start, stop, and reset the timing. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pendulum Clocks use the swinging motion of a pendulum to regulate the passage of time. These clocks were commonly used in the past for accurate timekeeping. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Quartz Clocks use the vibrations of a quartz crystal to regulate time. They are commonly found in both analog and digital formats. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Smartphones and Computers often include built-in clocks. These devices can synchronize with atomic clocks and provide accurate timekeeping. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nautical-Specific Time Measurements: Navigators and sailors have relied on specific time measurements to ensure safe and accurate maritime journeys. Two notable nautical-specific time measurements are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Greenwich Mean Time (GMT) is the mean solar time at the Prime Meridian, located at the Royal Observatory in Greenwich, England. Historically, GMT served as the standard reference time for navigation and was essential for calculating longitude accurately. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nautical Time: In the past, sailors aboard ships used nautical time to simplify timekeeping during their journeys. The day was divided into six four-hour watches, each indicated by the number of bells struck on the ship's bell. This system allowed for continuous operation and ensured crew members knew when to be on duty. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The choice of timekeeping instrument depends on factors such as accuracy requirements, portability, and intended use. Atomic clocks, based on the vibrations of atoms, are among the most accurate timekeeping devices developed to date. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> CONCLUSION </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The history of time measurement is a fascinating subject, from the ancient sundials to the modern atomic clocks. Today, the most accurate time measurement is based on the behavior of atoms. The definition of a second as the duration of 9,192,631,770 periods of radiation corresponding to the transition between the two hyperfine levels of the ground state of the cesium-133 atom is now the universally accepted standard. It is amazing to think that the behavior of an atom can be used to measure time with such incredible accuracy. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Area</Title>
         <item>
            <p> In mathematics and geometry, area refers to the measure of the amount of space within the boundary of a two-dimensional object. It is usually expressed in square units, such as square meters or square feet. The concept of area is used to quantify the extent or size of a flat surface. It quantifies the amount of space enclosed by a shape. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For example, if you have a rectangle with a length of <em>L</em> units and a width of <em>W</em> units, the area (<em>A</em>) of the rectangle is given by the formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>A</em>=<em>L</em>×<em>W</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the example shown, the area of the square is 12 square units because 12-unit squares are needed to cover the surface enclosed by the square. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Area Units</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image14.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 117-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The perimeter is defined as a measure of the length of the border that surrounds a closed geometric figure. The term perimeter derivates from the Greek words, ‘Peri’ and ‘meter’ which mean ‘around’ and ‘measure.’ In geometry, perimeter refers to the continuous line forming the path outside the two-dimensional shape. The area of a two-dimensional figure is defined as the amount of space inside the boundaries of the figure. It is a physical quantity that indicates the number of square units occupied by the two-dimensional object. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.4.2 Units for Measuring Area in Metric and US Standard </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Common units for measuring area include square meters, square feet, square kilometers, and acres, depending on the context and the scale of the area being measured. When working with area measurements, it's important to use the appropriate units based on the scale of the area being measured. For example, when designing a building, square footage is measured rather than square inches. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the US standard system, area is typically measured in square feet (ft²) or square inches (in²). To calculate the area of a rectangular or square surface, you multiply the length of one side by the length of the other side. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For example, the area of a rectangle with a length of 10 feet and a width of 5 feet is calculated as follows: Area = Length × Width Area = 10 ft × 5 ft = 50 ft², the conversion between two square units is the square of the conversion between the corresponding length units. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 foot = 12 inches, the relationship between square feet and square inches is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square foot = 144 square inches, where <m>{144in}^{2}</m>= 12 in × 12in. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Similarly, 1 square yard = 9 square feet,<m>{9ft}^{2}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square mile = 3,097,600 square yards = 27,878,400 square feet </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In addition, conversion factors include: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 inch = 2.54 cm </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <m>\frac{{1inch}^{2}}{{2.54cm}^{2}}</m>= <m>\frac{{1in}^{2}}{{6.4516cm}^{2}}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square inch = 6.4516 square centimeters </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square foot = 0.09290304 square meters </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square yard = 0.83612736 square meters </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 square mile = 2.589988110336 square kilometers </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The acre is also commonly used to measure land areas, where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 acre = 43,560 square feet = 4,840 square yards </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> An acre is approximately 40% of a hectare </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the metric system, area is measured in square meters (m²) or square centimeters (cm²). The formula for calculating the area of a rectangular or square surface remains the same, but the measurements are in metric units. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For instance, if you have a rectangular surface with a length of 8 meters and a width of 3 meters: Area = Length × Width Area = 8 m × 3 m = 24 m² </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Here are some common metric units for measuring area: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Square Millimeter (mm²): The square millimeter is an even smaller unit used for very small areas, often in microscopic or engineering applications. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Square Centimeter (cm²): The square centimeter is a smaller unit used for measuring smaller areas, especially in scientific contexts. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Square Meter (m²): The square meter is the base unit for area in the metric system. It is the area of a square with sides of one meter. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Square Kilometer (km²): The square kilometer is a larger unit of area often used for measuring large land areas, countries, or continents. One square kilometer is equal to 1,000,000 square meters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Hectare (ha): The hectare is commonly used for measuring land areas, especially in agriculture and forestry. One hectare is equal to 10,000 square meters or 0.01 square kilometers. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These units are part of the International System of Units (SI) and provide a standardized way to express measurements of area in the metric system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.4.3 Instruments Used to Measure Area </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Several instruments are used to measure area, depending on the context and the precision required. Here are some of them: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Rulers or Tape Measures are commonly used for measuring the lengths of sides of a shape, which can then be used to calculate the area of simple geometric shapes like rectangles and squares. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Tape Measure</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image15.jpeg"/>
               <!--Image of hands holding the Stanley PowerLock tape measure against a piece of wood, best tape measure 2022-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calipers are used for measuring the dimensions of small objects with precision, often used in manufacturing and engineering. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Dial Caliper</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image16.jpeg"/>
               <!--labelled diagram of a dial caliper-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Planimeter is a mechanical device used to measure the area of irregular shapes on a map or plan. It works by tracing the outline of the shape, and the device calculates the area based on the movement of its components. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Planimeter</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image17.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 1-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Measuring Wheel, also known as a surveyor's wheel, is a tool used to measure long distances on the ground. By rolling the wheel along a path, it records the number of rotations, which can then be used to calculate the area of a given area. Also known as a "measuring wheel" or "click wheel," surveyor's wheels are used to measure longer distances, such as those encountered in land surveying. They are often used for irregularly shaped areas. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Measuring Wheel </caption>
               <sidebyside width="30%" valign="bottom">
                  <image width="50%" source="images/image18.jpeg"/>
                  <image width="50%" source="images/image19.jpeg"/>
               </sidebyside>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> GIS Software, or Geographic Information Systems software, is used to analyze and measure areas of land, often for mapping purposes. These software applications can measure the area of polygons drawn on digital maps with high precision. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Geographic Information System (GIS)</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image20.jpeg"/>
               <!--GIS mapping tools hold the key to digitizing maps and plotting out complex sets of data.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Total Stations are electronic devices used in surveying and construction to measure distances and angles. They can also be used to calculate the area of land parcels by taking multiple measurements and applying mathematical algorithms. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Total Station</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image24.png"/>
               <!---A) Total station main parts (Topcon model GTS). B) Glass prism (model Leica). -->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Laser Distance Meters use laser technology to measure distances accurately. By taking measurements of the lengths of the sides of a shape, the area can be calculated. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Laser Distance Meter</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image21.jpeg"/>
               <!--Laser Tape Measuring-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Satellite Imagery or Global Positioning System (GPS) remote sensing technologies are used to measure large areas of land from space. Advanced algorithms process satellite data to calculate the area of land parcels, monitor changes over time, and conduct environmental assessments. It provides accurate location data that can be used to calculate area. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Satellite Imagery GPS</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image22.jpeg"/>
               <!--The ICESat-2 mission will measure the changing height of Earth's glaciers, ice sheets and sea ice, one laser pulse at a time, 10,000 laser pulses per second.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Navigation Charts are one of the most fundamental tools available to the mariner. A navigation chart is a map that depicts the configuration of the shoreline and seafloor. It provides water depths, locations of dangers to navigation, locations and characteristics of aids to navigation, anchorages, and other features. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Navigation Chart Scale is an essential tool for mariners, indicating coastlines, depths, and navigational hazards. The scale of a navigation chart relates distance on the chart to distance in the real world. For example, a scale of 1:50,000 means that one unit of length on the chart (e.g., 1 inch) represents 50,000 units of the same length in the real world (e.g., 50,000 inches or approximately 0.8 nautical miles). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The navigation chart is essential for safe navigation. Mariners use charts to plan voyages and navigate ships safely and economically. Federal regulations require most commercial vessels to carry electronic or paper navigation charts while they transit U.S. waters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Since the mid-1830s, the U.S. Coast Survey (a NOAA predecessor agency) has been the nation’s navigation chart maker. NOAA's Office of Coast Survey is still responsible for creating and maintaining all charts of U.S. coastal waters, the Great Lakes, and waters surrounding U.S. territories. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Navigation Chart</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image23.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 1212727181-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bathymetric Charts focus on the depths and contours of underwater surfaces. These charts provide valuable information for marine engineering projects and navigation, allowing engineers to assess the seabed's topography and plan accordingly. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Bathymetric Map</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image24.jpeg"/>
               <!--How to create bathymetric map in ArcGIS #gistutorial #bathymetricmap #lakevolume-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These are just a few examples of instruments and technologies used to measure area, each suited to different applications and levels of precision. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.4.4 Area in Math </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> There are several well-known formulas for the areas of simple shapes such as triangles, rectangles, and circles. Using these formulas, the area of any polygon can be found by dividing the polygon into triangles. For shapes with a curved boundary, calculus is usually required to compute the area. Indeed, the problem of determining the area of plane figures was a major motivation for the historical development of calculus. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mathematics provides various formulas and methods to find the area of different shapes and surfaces. Here are some common mathematical approaches: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Geometric Formulas: For basic shapes like rectangles, squares, triangles, circles, and polygons, there are well-known formulas to calculate their areas. For instance: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Area of a square: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the area of a square, multiply the length of one side by the other (equal length sides). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Area = a2</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image25.png"/>
               <!--Picture 116-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> a = length of side </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Area of a rectangle: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the area of a rectangle, multiply the width by the height. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Area = w × h</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image26.png"/>
               <!--Picture 115-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> w = width </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> h = height </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Area of Triangle: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the area of a triangle, multiply <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> the base times the height. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Area = ½ × b × h</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image27.png"/>
               <!--Picture 114-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> b = base </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> h = vertical height </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Area of Circle: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the area of a circle, multiply the radius squared by π=3,.14. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Area = π × r2</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image28.png"/>
               <!--Picture 113-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> r = radius </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Integration: For irregular shapes or curves, calculus can be used. By integrating appropriate functions over a given interval, you can find the area under a curve or between curves. This method is particularly useful for finding the area of regions bounded by curves in the Cartesian coordinate system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dissection and Composition: This method involves decomposing complex shapes into simpler shapes whose areas are known. For example, a complex shape might be divided into rectangles, triangles, circles, etc., and then the areas of these simpler shapes are calculated individually and summed up to find the total area. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Coordinate Geometry: In the Cartesian coordinate system, the area of a polygon can be calculated using the shoelace formula or by dividing the polygon into triangles and summing their areas. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Vector Calculus: In three-dimensional space, vector calculus can be used to find the area of surfaces. For example, the surface area of a parametrically defined surface can be found using a surface integral. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Limit Process: The area of a shape can also be approximated using a limit process, where you divide the shape into smaller and smaller pieces and sum their areas. As the size of the pieces approaches zero, the sum converges to the exact area of the shape. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These are just a few examples of how mathematics can be used to find area, and there are many other techniques and methods depending on the specific shape or surface being considered. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Volume</Title>
         <item>
            <p> Volume is the amount of three-dimensional space an object or substance occupies. It is a scalar quantity, meaning it has magnitude but no direction. The concept of volume is used to quantify the extent of a region in space and is typically expressed in cubic units. Volume measures capacity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.5.2 Units for Measuring Volume </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These are some of the most commonly used units for measuring volume, but there are others as well, depending on specific contexts and regions. Also, there may be <em>dry</em> or <em>wet</em> measures of volume. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard System: In the US standard system, volume is typically measured in cubic feet (ft³) or cubic inches (in³). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The primary units for measuring volume include: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cubic Inch (in³): The cubic inch is a small unit of volume commonly used in engineering and manufacturing contexts. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cubic Foot (ft³): The cubic foot is a larger unit of volume often used in construction and real estate. One cubic foot is equivalent to the volume of a cube with sides of one foot. There are 1,728 cubic inches in one cubic foot. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Fluid Ounce (fl oz): The fluid ounce is commonly used for measuring liquid volumes, especially in the context of beverages and cooking. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pint (pt): The pint is a unit of liquid volume. In the U.S., there are two types of pints: the liquid pint (equal to 16 fluid ounces) and the dry pint (used for measuring dry goods). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Quart (qt): The quart is a unit of liquid volume. Like the pint, there are two types: the liquid quart (equal to 32 fluid ounces) and the dry quart. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gallon (gal): The gallon is a larger unit of liquid volume, equal to 128 fluid ounces. 1 US gallon is equivalent to 231 cubic inches. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image25.jpeg"/>
               <!--Picture 2073195406-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Barrel: The amount of liquid a barrel contains can vary depending on the type of barrel and its size. The most common types of barrels used for liquids are oil barrels and whiskey barrels. The standard size for an oil barrel is 42 US gallons (approximately 159 liters). However, there are also other sizes used in different regions and industries. It’s important to note that the capacity of a barrel can vary depending on its construction and specific dimensions, but these are the standard sizes for these types of barrels. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Barrels</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image26.jpeg"/>
               <!--Barrel-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Drum: one common size is the 55-gallon drum, which is prevalent for industrial and commercial use. This drum can hold approximately 55 US gallons of liquid, which is roughly equivalent to 208 liters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Drums</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image27.jpeg"/>
               <!--Made in USA - 55 Gal Drum Storage Rack | MSC Industrial Supply Co.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric System: The standard unit for measuring volume in the International System of Units (SI) is the cubic meter (m³) or cubic centimeters (cm³). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Similar to the US standard system, the volume of regular-shaped objects is determined by multiplying the three dimensions in metric units. For example, if you have a rectangular prism with dimensions 2 meters by 4 meters by 1 meter: Volume = Length × Width × Height Volume = 2 m × 4 m × 1 m = 8 m³ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the metric system, volume is typically measured using the liter (L) as the standard unit. The liter is equivalent to 1 cubic decimeter (dm³). The cubic meter (m³) is the standard unit for larger volumes. Here are some common metric units for measuring volume: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cubic Meter (m³): The cubic meter is the SI unit for volume and is equal to the volume of a cube with sides of one meter. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Liter (L): The liter is commonly used for everyday measurements of liquid volumes. One liter is equal to 1 cubic decimeter. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Milliliter (mL): The milliliter is a smaller unit used for precise measurements of liquids. One milliliter is equal to one-thousandth of a liter. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cubic Centimeter (cm³): The cubic centimeter is often used in scientific and medical contexts for measuring the volume of small objects or substances. It is equivalent to one milliliter. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In summary, the liter is the most common unit for expressing volume in the metric system, especially in everyday situations. The cubic meter is used for larger volumes, and smaller units like milliliters and cubic centimeters are used for more precise measurements. The metric system provides a straightforward and decimal-based system for measuring volumes, making it widely adopted in scientific and everyday applications around the world. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The Ton: A Ton has a long history and has acquired several meanings and uses. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Depending on context, a ton may refer to a unit measure of mass, volume or force. For volume, it could be a dry or wet measure. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In transportation, one metric ton can be equal to one cubic meter (CBM) of volume. A CBM is a unit of measurement used in the shipping and transportation industries to show how much space a shipment takes up: 1 meter x 1 meter x 1 meter (or 1 cubic meter). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The amount of liquid that one ton contains depends on the density of the liquid. Density is a measure of how much mass is contained in a given volume. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density is <em>the ratio of the mass to the volume</em> of a substance: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density =<m>\frac{Mass}{Volume}</m> = ρ = m / V </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density of Water - US System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mass (m) refers to the amount of water measured in pounds (lbs.). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Volume (V) refers to the volume of water measured in cubic feet (ft³). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One cubic foot of water weighs 62.4 lbs. @ 39.2°F </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density =<m>\frac{Mass}{Volume}</m>= 62.4 lbs. =<m>\frac{62.4lbs}{{1ft}^{3}}</m> = 62.4 lb./ft³ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density (ρ, rho): The density of water in pounds per cubic foot (lbs./ft³) is 62.4 lbs./ft³ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density of Water Metric System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One cubic meter of water weighs 1000 kilograms (kg) @ 4°C </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Volume equals one cubic meter </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Density = <m>\frac{1000kg}{{1m}^{3}}</m> = 1000 kg/<m>m^{3}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>English or Long Ton = 2240 lb. (1016.05 kg)</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>American or Short Ton' = 2000 lb. (907.18 kg)</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Tonne or Metric Ton' = 1000 kg (2204.62 lb.)</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Measurement or Shipping Ton = 1 cubic meter.</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> So, the volume of one ton of liquid depends on the density of the particular liquid you're considering. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.5.3 Instruments for Measuring Volume </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> When dealing with regular-shaped objects like cubes or rectangular prisms, you calculate the volume by multiplying the length, width, and height of the object. For instance, the volume of a cube with sides measuring 3 feet each is calculated as follows: Volume = Length × Width × Height Volume = 3 ft × 3 ft × 3 ft = 27 ft³. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Various instruments are used to measure volume, and the choice of instrument depends on the nature of the substance being measured (solid, liquid, or gas) and the required level of precision. Here are some common measuring instruments for determining volume: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Graduated Cylinder is a cylindrical container marked with calibrated lines to indicate volume. It is commonly used in laboratories to measure the volume of liquids. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image28.jpeg"/>
               <!--Measurement Uncertainty, Accuracy, and Precision (1.5) – Chemistry 110-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Beakers are cylindrical or conical containers with volume markings. While they are not as precise as graduated cylinders, they are often used for approximate volume measurements. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Beaker</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image29.jpeg"/>
               <!--beaker - list of lab equipment-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pipettes are calibrated glass or plastic tubes used to measure and transfer small volumes of liquids with high precision. There are different types, including volumetric pipettes and micropipettes. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Pipettes</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image29.png"/>
               <!--Picture 1243325601-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A burette is a long, graduated tube with a valve at the bottom. It is commonly used in analytical chemistry for precise dispensing of liquids. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Burette</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image30.jpeg"/>
               <!--Glass Burette - PTFE Stopcock (Class B) - 50ml-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A gas syringe is used to measure the volume of gases in chemical reactions. The plunger is pushed or pulled to change the volume, and the graduations on the syringe indicate the volume of the gas. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/gas-syringe.png"/>
               <!--Collecting Gas using a Gas Syringe-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Geometric Instruments (for Irregular Shapes): For irregularly shaped objects, displacement methods or geometric instruments like Archimedes' principle can be used to determine volume. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Laser scanners use laser technology to create a three-dimensional point cloud representation of an object's surface. By analyzing the point cloud, engineers can calculate the object's volume with high accuracy. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 6.5.4 Volume Measurements Aboard Ship </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the nautical world, understanding volume measurements is crucial for various maritime activities and engineering projects. Two nautical-specific volume measurements are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Displacement Volume: In naval architecture, displacement volume refers to the volume of water displaced by a floating vessel, such as a ship or boat. It is an essential measurement for determining a vessel's buoyancy and stability. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cargo Capacity: For shipping and maritime logistics, measuring the cargo capacity of a vessel is vital. It involves calculating the available space inside the ship to transport goods, ensuring efficient and safe cargo handling. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Along with these are the measurements of various liquids held in tanks aboard ships. To determine this we use <em>soundings.</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> What is Sounding? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Checking the level of the fluid in a tank is considered part of the sounding process on ship. The final sounding value of the tank is the total quantity of fluid (oil, bilge, sludge, or water) inside a ship’s tank. The initial process is to first measure the depth of the fluid from the surface to the bottom of the tank by using sounding tape. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The sounding tape value is later used in calculation of the final sounding value, which is derived using the sounding table, taking the list and trim of the ship into account and the temperature at which the fluid (specifically for oil) is stored (as density of oil is affected by temperature). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Importance of Sounding </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Is it necessary to take soundings of various tanks every day? Yes. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In some cases, the sounding has to be taken in every watch. A ship is a floating factory with several mechanical systems working continuously. These systems require fuel oil, lube oil and water to operate, and these fluids are consumed from service tanks or sump tanks. The service and sump tanks on a ship need to be sounded every watch to ensure the level is maintained. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The service tanks and sump tanks levels are maintained by filling them up with appropriate fluid using storage tanks, which are sounded once in a day. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The four most important operations which are dependent on the sounding values are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Stability of the Ship: The ship stability highly depends on how various fluids (oil, water, fluid cargo etc.) are stored to tackle the free surface effect, which is a very important factor for defining ship’s stability </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Voyage Planning: The current volume of fluids (oil, water etc.) in various tanks and the estimated volume needed to reach the next port or complete a voyage needs to be known before the ship sails. This is to ensure a minimum quantity is always maintained even when a ship is diverted to a longer route so that the essential fluids used to run machinery and systems do not get consumed early, which may leave the ship stranded. Also, to plan bunkering of fuel or receiving of fuel, vendors need to be notified well ahead of time for making arrangements in preferred port of call, hence sounding of all tanks in a ship is very important. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cargo Planning: The cargo loading and arrangement of the cargo at different bays or holds are performed by the planner based on the current stability of the ship. The knowledge of volume in various tanks is important to perform this task to avoid damage to the ship structure and to avoid any other risk to ship’s stability. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For Assessing Leakages/Loss: Regular monitoring and keeping record of sounding for tanks containing oil and water is necessary for detecting unwanted leakages or loss of content from the tank. For example, if an oil storage tank which is not in use shows a decrease in the sounding value, it might be due to an open/malfunctioning valve of the tank or due to leakage from the tank. Also, the sounding values of service tanks in the engine room are used to determine the fuel/lube oil consumption by machinery. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Methods for taking sounding on a ship </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Certain cargos carried on ships are toxic, hazardous and inflammable, hence various methods are provided on a ship to measure the volume in the tank. Some of the most common gauging methods used on ships are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Manual sounding </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> All important tanks on ships are provided with sounding tubes through which a person can insert a sounding tape to measure the level in the tank manually. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Sounding tape comes in meters or feet and is normally made up of brass and steel with a weighted bob attached at the end of the tape using a strap hook. See <xref ref="sounding-tape-1"/> and <xref ref="sounding-tape-2"/>. Sounding tape is the most commonly used method used for calculation of tank capacity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="sounding-tape-1">
               <caption>Sounding Tape with Ullage and Plumb (Innage) bobs.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image31.jpeg"/>
               <!--Content Placeholder 5-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="sounding-tape-2">
               <caption>Sounding Tape with Innage Bob and Grounding Strap</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image30.png"/>
               <!--Content Placeholder 5-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Innage Sounding Value is the measure from the top of the liquid to the bottom of the sounding tube (using innage/plumb bob). See <xref ref="sounding-innage"/>below. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="sounding-innage">
               <caption>Innage Sounding</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image31.png"/>
               <!--Content Placeholder 4-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Ullage Sounding Value is the measure from the top of the liquid (using ullage bob) to the top of the sounding tube. See <xref ref="sounding-ullage"/>. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="sounding-ullage">
               <caption>Ullage Sounding</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image32.png"/>
               <!--Content Placeholder 5-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Electronic Sounding Gauges: In electronic sounding, a sensor is used which senses the pressure inside the sounding pipe or by sensing the tank pressure and sends a signal to the receiver. Here the signal is translated to the tank’s content value with the help of a PLC circuit. The value is displayed using an electrically operated servo gauge or electrical capacitance gauge. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Electrically Powered Servo-Operated Gauges: This tank gauging system is based on the principle of displacement measurement. A small displacer is accurately positioned in the liquid medium using a servo motor. The displacer is suspended on a measuring wire that is wound onto a finely grooved drum housing within the instrument. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pneumercator (Bubbler) Gauges: This gauging system works on the principle of hydrostatic pressure measurement to determine liquid level. The pressure created by the actual depth of liquid is fed to the gauge which moves the reading until an equilibrium is reached. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Pneumercator (Bubbler) Gage</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image32.jpeg"/>
               <!--Content Placeholder 7-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Ultrasonic Gauges: This works on principle similar to that of an echo sounder wherein an ultrasonic wave is thrown from the gauge. The sensor detects the echo from the surface and routes it back to the microprocessor for a digital representation of the distance between the sensor and the surface level. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Sounding Gauges: Mechanical provisions are made inside the tank so that the quantity of a tank can directly be read through a level marker, an indicator, or a float level sensor. In the tank a float can be attached to a pointer through a pulley. As the level varies, the pointer reading will change accordingly. A level gauge glass is also attached to the tank to read the quantity of the fluid inside the tank. The gauge may also be a pneumatic/hydraulic operated gauge or differential pressure gauge. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bunkering or Taking on Fuel Oil Aboard Ship </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Bunker Calculation: Bunker quantity calculations are critical calculations which every marine engineer should be familiar with throughout his/her career. Bunker fuel, being a highly valued product, has to be very carefully and accurately calculated for determining the quantity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The volume of a definite quantity of bunker increases with an increase in temperature whereas its weight remains the same. For this reason, the bunker is always ordered and measured in weight and not by volume. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The density of fuel oil (in kg/<m>m^{3}</m>) at a standard reference temperature of 15⁰C is always provided by the supplier in <em>Bunker Delivery Note</em>. With this, the density of fuel oil at tank temperature can be determined using an ASTM table or using software most commonly installed on all ship’s computer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>ASTM Table</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image33.png"/>
               <!--marine cargo ship surveyors-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Bunker Weight</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image34.png"/>
               <!--tank weight-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> FORMULAS for Calculating Volume of different shapes </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The method for measuring volume depends on the shape of the object. For simple shapes like cubes, rectangular prisms, cylinders, and spheres, there are specific formulas you can use. For example: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Cube: The volume of a cube or rectangular prism is calculated by multiplying the length, width, and height. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The volume, V, of a <em>cube</em> with edge, s, is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> V = s<m>3</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Cylinder</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image35.png"/>
               <!--Picture 112-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The volume of a cylinder is calculated by multiplying the area of its base (usually a circle) by its height. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> V = π r<m>2</m> h </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where r is the radius of the base and h is the height of the cylinder. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Sphere</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image36.png"/>
               <!--Picture 111-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The volume, V, of a sphere with radius, r, is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The volume of a sphere is calculated using the formula V = (4/3) πr<m>3</m>. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>For irregularly shaped objects, you can use techniques like water displacement, where you submerge the object in water and measure the volume of water displaced.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image37.png"/>
               <!--Picture 110-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>For irregularly shaped objects, you can use techniques like water displacement, where you submerge the object in water and measure the volume of water displaced.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image38.png"/>
               <!--Picture 109-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Examples of Volume (capacity) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The basic unit of volume in the metric system is a cube, 10 centimeters on each side. Contained in this cube are 1,000 cubic centimeters or one liter. A liter contains slightly more liquid than a quart. Very large volumes may be measured in cubic meters (1 cubic meter = about 264 gallons). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Liquid Measure</em>
               <!-- linebreak -->1 liter = 1.057 (1) quart<!-- linebreak -->1 quart = .9464 (1) liter<!-- linebreak -->1 liter = .2642 (.25) gallons<!-- linebreak -->1 gallon = 3.785 (4) liters<!-- linebreak -->1 dekaliter (dal) = 2.642 (2.5) gallons </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Dry Measure</em>
               <!-- linebreak -->1 cubic meter = 1.308 (1.3) cubic yards<!-- linebreak -->1 cubic yard = .7646 (.76) cubic meters<!-- linebreak -->1 bushel = 1.244 (1.25) cubic feet<!-- linebreak -->1 bushel = .0352 (.035) cubic meters<!-- linebreak -->1 cubic meter = 28.38 (30) bushels </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Understanding volume is essential in various scientific fields, including physics, chemistry, engineering, and biology. It is used to describe the capacity of containers, the displacement of fluids, the size of objects, and many other aspects of spatial measurements. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In summary, you can calculate volume using specific formulas depending on the shape of the object. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mastering the concept of volume will be indispensable in your engineering endeavors. Whether you're designing structures, analyzing fluid flows, or working on nautical projects, understanding volume measurements will enable you to tackle complex challenges and create innovative solutions that shape the world around us. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title> Torque </Title>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>INTRODUCTION</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque is a measure of the force that can cause an object to rotate about an axis. The example of opening a door offers an intuitive understanding of torque. When a person opens a door, they push on the side of the door farthest from the hinges. Pushing on the side closest to the hinges requires considerably more force. Although the work done is the same in both cases (the larger force would be applied over a smaller distance), people generally prefer to apply less force, hence the usual location of the door handle. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque is the rotational equivalent of force. It is the measure of the tendency of a force to rotate an object around an axis of rotation. In simpler terms, torque is the turning force that causes an object to rotate, turn or twist. Imagine you're trying to turn a wheel. You need to apply a force to make it spin, right? Torque is the measure of how much force you need to apply to make an object rotate around a turning point. It's measured in Newton meters, or foot-pounds, which is a fancy way of saying how hard you need to push on something and how far away from the turning point you are. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Example of Torque, Screwdriver turning a screw</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image39.png"/>
               <!--Picture 1-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Different terminologies, such as moment or moment of force, are interchangeably used to describe torque. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The distance of the point of application of force from the axis of rotation is called the moment arm or lever arm. See figure below. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Moment Arm</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image40.png"/>
               <!--Picture 83-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Direction of Torque </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Understanding the direction of torque is crucial in analyzing rotational dynamics, ensuring the correct application of forces in mechanical systems, and solving problems involving rotational motion. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Direction of torque</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image33.jpeg"/>
               <!--C:\Users\rgill.MARITIME-EDU\AppData\Local\Microsoft\Windows\INetCache\Content.MSO\A2392C1B.tmp-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Wrench Turning a Bolt: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> If you apply the force to turn the bolt clockwise, the torque vector points downwards. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> If you apply a force to a wrench to turn a bolt counterclockwise, the torque vector points upwards. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Rotating a Wheel </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> As torque is a vector quantity, both magnitude and direction are needed to define it. The direction of torque can be found using the right-hand rule, where four fingers of the right hand are pointed in the direction of the force F that is applied. The direction of the torque is the same as the direction of the thumb. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> If a force applied to the edge of a wheel causes it to rotate counterclockwise, the torque vector points out of the plane (perpendicular to the wheel's surface). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> If the force causes the wheel to rotate clockwise, the torque vector points into the plane. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Right Hand Rule</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image41.png"/>
               <!--Picture 81-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 2.2 Units of Torque </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard System: In the US standard system, torque is typically measured in foot-pounds (ft-lb) or inch-pounds (in-lbs.). These units represent the amount of force applied at a specified distance from the rotational axis. For example, one foot-pound of torque is equal to a force of one pound applied at a distance of one foot from the axis of rotation. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric System: In the metric system, torque is measured in newton-meters (N-m) or in some cases, newton-centimeters (N-cm). The newton-meter represents the force (in newtons) applied at a distance of one meter from the rotational axis. Similarly, the newton-centimeter is the force (in newtons) applied at a distance of one centimeter from the axis of rotation. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Units of Torque in Foot-Pounds and Newton-Meters</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image42.png"/>
               <!--Picture 77-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Work and Torque </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Like work, torque is a force multiplied by a distance. However, the difference lies in how force and distance are multiplied, and what kind of distance is used in this scenario. For work, the force (<em>F</em>) and the distance (<em>d</em>) are multiplied by a dot product. Because it is the dot product of two vectors, it is a scalar value. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>W</em>=<em>F</em>⋅ <em>d</em>=<em>F d cos θ</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Let’s clarify the difference with examples. If there is a box and I am pushing it horizontally, I am doing work on it. If I push it onto an inclined plane to load it onto the back of a truck, it’s still work because the box is not fixed on any particular axis. However, if I take that box and put it on one end of a seesaw, with myself standing at the other, both the box and I are applying torques on the seesaw. The seesaw’s fulcrum fixes it on an axis that causes rotational motion. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torques, however, involve rotation along a fixed axis. Therefore, instead of a dot product, we need to use a cross product. We also can’t use the distance d that we applied in the previous work equation because we are not displacing the object a certain distance. We are rotating it along a fixed axis. To calculate torque, we must introduce a new vector, <em>r</em> (radius). Physically, <em>r</em> is the distance from the axis of rotation to the point where the force is applied. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>τ</em>=<em>r</em> ×<em>F</em>= <em>r F sin θ</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque (τ⃗) is calculated using the cross product of the position vector (r⃗) and the force vector (F⃗): </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Magnitude of Torque: τ= r⋅ F ⋅ sin (θ) where θ is the angle between the position vector and the force vector. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Direction of Torque: The direction of τ⃗ is given by the right-hand rule as described above. It is perpendicular to the plane formed by r⃗ and F⃗ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque Formula is given by the cross product between Force and the displacement vector from the pivot point. Thus, mathematically torque can be written as: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Torque = Force × Displacement Vector</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>OR</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque (τ) = Force (F) × Distance (r) × sin (θ) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Where θ is the angle between vector r and vector F.</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ is the torque. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F is the force applied. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> r is the distance from the axis of rotation to the point where the force is applied. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> θ is the angle between the lever arm and the direction of the force. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Torque Formula</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image43.png"/>
               <!--Torque Measurement -->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Torque Formula with Values</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image44.png"/>
               <!--Examples of Torque-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the above diagram: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F = 5 N </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> r = 4 m </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> sin θ = 30° </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Putting in these values we have, </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ = 5 x 4 x sin 30° </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ = 10 N · m </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example 1 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A mechanic applies a force of 400N to a wrench for loosening a bolt. He applies the force which is perpendicular to the arm of the wrench. The distance between the bolt to the hand is 60cm. Find out the torque applied. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solution: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> As mentioned in the question that the applied force is perpendicular to the arm of wrench so, the angle will be 90°. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F = 400N </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> r = 60cm = 60⁄100 = .60 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque = F × distance × sin θ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ = F × r × sin 90° </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ = 400 × 0.60 × 1 [sin 90° = 1] </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> τ = 240 Nm </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Therefore, the magnitude of torque will be 240 Nm. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Example 2</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calculate the Torque on an object from a Force applied at an angle </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A wrench is loosening a bolt, the force applied is 25 Newtons at an angle of 60 degrees relative to the wrench. If the wrench is 30 centimeters long and the force is applied at the end of the wrench, what is the Torque on the bolt? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Length of lever arm, r, = 30 centimeters, 0.3 meters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Force = 25 Newtons </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Angle Force makes with wrench is 60 degrees </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque = r x F x sin () </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque = 30cm x 25N x sin <m>60^{0}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> sin <m>60^{0} =</m>0.86 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> T = 6.5 NM </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 2.3 Instruments Used to Measure Torque </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque Wrench: A torque wrench is a precision tool commonly used to apply a specific amount of torque to fasteners such as nuts and bolts. It has a calibrated scale that allows engineers to set the desired torque value, ensuring accurate and consistent tightening </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Torque Wrench</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image45.png"/>
               <!--Picture 74-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A torque wrench has a calibrated scale or a digital display that allows the user to set and control the applied torque accurately. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque Sensors: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque sensors are devices that measure the torque applied to an object or produced by a rotating system. These sensors can be integrated into machinery or used as standalone devices to provide real-time torque measurements. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamometers: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A Prony brake is a friction brake and torque-measuring system that was invented by French mathematician and engineer Gaspard de Prony in 1821. The term "brake horsepower" is one measurement of power derived from this method of measuring torque. (Power is calculated by multiplying torque by rotational speed.) It's also known as an absorption dynamometer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Prony Brake Dynamometer</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image46.png"/>
               <!--Picture 73-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 2.4 Types of Torque </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Torque can be either static or dynamic </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Static Torque is the force needed to initiate movement from a standstill or to stop an already moving object. It’s the amount of Torque required to overcome the inertia of a stationary object and start its rotation. This concept is commonly used in scenarios where an object needs to be moved from a rest position, such as starting a car engine or unscrewing a tightly fixed bolt. A person pushing a closed-door is applying a static torque because the door isn’t rotating despite the force applied. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Static Torque: Turning a bolt</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/torque-on-bolt.png"/>
               <!--Torque is related to bolt tightness, but many additional factors, such as friction, combined into a single nut factor, can have a significant impact on the relationship of torque to the tightness of the bolted joint.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamic Torque refers to the twisting force that maintains an object’s constant rotational motion once it has started moving. This type of torque is used to accelerate or decelerate a moving object, such as a wheel or a motor. It’s the Torque necessary to keep an object spinning at a steady rate, overcoming any frictional forces acting against it. Dynamic Torque is often used in the context of continually operating systems, like turbines in a power plant or motors in electric appliances. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example Usage </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamic Torque: Running a motor </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamic Torque: Torque to maintain rotation </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The drive shaft in a racing car accelerating from the start line exhibits dynamic torque because it must be producing an angular acceleration of the wheels, given that the car is accelerating along the track. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> How can we increase or decrease torque? </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> It is often necessary to increase or decrease the torque produced by a motor to suit different applications. Recall that the length of a <em>lever</em> can increase or decrease the force on an object at the expense of the distance through which the lever must be pushed. Similarly, the torque produced by a motor can be increased or decreased through the use of gearing. An increase in torque comes with a proportional decrease in rotational speed. The meshing of two gear teeth can be viewed as equivalent to the interaction of a pair of levers as shown in <xref ref="gear-ratio"/>. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gear Ratio </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> When a larger gear drives a smaller one, for one rotation of the larger gear the small gear must complete more revolutions - so the output will be faster than the input. If the situation is reversed, and a smaller gear drives a larger output gear, then for one rotation of the input the output will complete less than one revolution – so the output will be slower than the input. The ratio of the sizes of the two gears is proportional to the speed and torque changes between them. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="gear-ratio">
               <caption>Gear Ratios </caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image47.png"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section">
         <Title>Power</Title>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Power</em> is defined as the amount of energy used per unit time or rate of doing work. It has the units of watt, Btu, horsepower, or ft-lb/sec. Power is a measure of the rate at which energy is used. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Regarding work, when you lift a weight of 1 pound through a distance of 1 foot, you have done 1 foot-pound of <em>work,</em> regardless of whether you do it in half a second or half an hour. A device which can do a lot of work quickly is powerful. Power, however, is time dependent. Therefore, if you lift that same 1-pound weight over the same distance more quickly, you are more powerful! </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The common unit of measurement for power is the <em>horsepower</em> (hp). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power is a critical physical quantity that defines the rate at which work is done or energy is transferred or converted. In the world of engineering, power plays a significant role in designing efficient systems, analyzing energy consumption, and optimizing engineering solutions. Understanding power and its measurement is essential for creating sustainable technologies, enhancing performance, and addressing real-world challenges. Let's explore how power is measured in both the US standard and metric systems, the instruments used for measurement, and any nautical-specific measurements related to power. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Forms of Power </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the context of science, power can refer to different concepts depending on the specific field or application. Here are several forms of power in various scientific contexts: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power: In classical mechanics, mechanical power is the rate at which work is done or energy is transferred. It is the product of force and velocity. Mechanical power is the term used to describe when work is being done. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Electrical Power: In electrical systems, power is the rate at which electrical energy is transferred or converted. It is measured in watts and is the product of voltage and current. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermal Power: In thermodynamics, thermal power refers to the rate at which heat energy is transferred or converted. It is often measured in watts and is associated with processes involving temperature differentials. Thermal power is the term used to refer to the transfer of heat. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nuclear Power: In the context of nuclear physics, power can refer to the rate of energy release in nuclear reactions. Nuclear power is harnessed in nuclear reactors for electricity generation. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solar Power: This is a form of power derived from the sun's radiation. Solar power can be harnessed through various technologies such as photovoltaic cells and solar thermal systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Wind Power: Wind power is the conversion of wind energy into a useful form, typically electricity, using wind turbines. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Hydraulic Power: In fluid dynamics, hydraulic power is associated with the movement and pressure of fluids. It is often utilized in hydraulic systems for various applications. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Chemical Power: In chemistry, chemical reactions can release or store energy. Chemical power is associated with the energy changes in chemical reactions. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Muscular Power: In biology and biomechanics, muscular power refers to the rate at which work is done by muscles. It is often expressed in terms of force and velocity of muscle contraction. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Photon Power: In optics, the power of a lens is a measure of its ability to converge or diverge light. It is often measured in diopters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> UNITS of POWER </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power is measured in various units depending on the context and the system of measurement being used. The standard unit of power in the International System of Units (SI) is the watt (W). Here are some common units of power: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Watt (W): The watt is the SI unit of power and is defined as one joule per second. It is named after James Watt, a Scottish engineer. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Kilowatt (kW): One kilowatt is equal to 1,000 watts. It is commonly used in the context of electrical power, especially in the rating of appliances and electrical systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Megawatt (MW): One megawatt is equal to 1 million watts or 1,000 kilowatts. This unit is often used in the context of large-scale power generation and distribution. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Gigawatt (GW): One gigawatt is equal to 1 billion watts or 1,000 megawatts. It is commonly used to express the capacity of power plants or large energy systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calories per Second (cal/s or kcal/s): In some contexts, especially in the field of nutrition and metabolic studies, power can be expressed in terms of calories per second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> BTU per Hour (BTU/h): In the field of heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC), power is sometimes measured in British Thermal Units per hour. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower (hp): Horsepower is a unit of power that is still used in various industries, particularly in the context of engines and motors. One horsepower is approximately equal to 745.7 watts. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Foot-Pound per Minute (ft-lb/min): This unit is often used in the context of mechanical power, where work is done over time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> These units provide a way to quantify and compare the rate at which energy is transferred or converted in various scientific and engineering applications. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the context of mechanics and engineering, mechanical power refers to the rate at which work is done or energy is transferred within a mechanical system. It is a measure of how quickly energy is used or produced in a mechanical process. The unit of mechanical power is the watt (W). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Measurement of Power:</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Standard System: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the US standard system, power is typically measured in horsepower (hp). One horsepower is equivalent to 550 foot-pounds per second (ft-lb/s) or approximately 746 watts. It is a common unit used to express the power output of engines, motors, and other mechanical systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> One mechanical horsepower is defined as the ability to do 550 foot-pounds of work per second. In other words, if a machine can exert a force of 550 pounds over a distance of one foot in one second, it is considered to have a power output of 1 mechanical horsepower. This definition was based on Watt's observations of the work done by draft horses in coal mines and was intended to provide a meaningful measure of power that people could relate to in the late 18th century. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> While the original concept of horsepower was rooted in the comparison to the work done by horses, it has become a standard unit of power used in various industries, particularly in the automotive and mechanical engineering fields, to express the power output of engines and motors. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> By definition, 1 horsepower is equal to 33,000 foot-pounds of work per minute or 550 foot-pounds of work per second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thus, a machine that is capable of doing 550 foot-pounds of work per second is said to be a 1-horsepower machine. (As you can see, your horsepower rating would not be very impressive if you did 1 foot-pound of work in half an hour. Figure it out. It works out to be just a little more than one-millionth of a horsepower.) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower (hp) is a unit of measurement in the foot-pound-second (fps or ft-lb/s) or English system, sometimes used to express the rate at which mechanical energy is expended. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>A horse produces approximately one horsepower</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image48.png"/>
               <!--Horsepower - Wikipedia-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric System: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the metric system, power is measured in watts (W). One watt is defined as one joule per second (J/s), representing the rate at which work is done or energy is transferred. The watt is the standard unit for expressing power in the International System of Units (SI). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the International System of Units (SI), power is typically measured in watts. One mechanical horsepower is equivalent to approximately 745.7 watts. The conversion factor is often rounded to 746 watts for practical use. So, when you see a power rating for an engine or motor in horsepower, it represents the mechanical power output of that device. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power Formulas </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The formula for mechanical power is derived from the basic definition of power: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power (P)=<m>\frac{Work(w)}{Time(t)}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> ​Alternatively, if the system involves a force (F) acting over a distance (d), the formula for mechanical power can be expressed as: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em>=<m>\frac{Fxd}{t}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> ​In this formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em> is the mechanical power </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>W</em> is the work done, </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>F</em> is the force applied, </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>d</em> is the distance over which the force is applied, </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>t</em> is the time taken. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical energy used per unit time is called <em>mechanical power</em>. Mechanical power is the rate at which work is done. Mechanical power is expressed in units of joules/sec (joules/s) or a watt (W) in the metric system, and feet - pounds force per second (ft-lbf/s) or horsepower (hp) in the English system. Mechanical power can be calculated using the following mathematical expression. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power= <m>\frac{WorkDone}{Timerequired}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Because work can be defined as force times distance, we can also use the following equation: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em>=<m>\frac{Fxd}{t}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> ) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">P</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">=</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">Power (W or ft-lb/s)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">F</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">=</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">Force (N or lb)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">d</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">=</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">distance (m or ft)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell halign="left">t</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">=</cell>
                     <cell halign="left">time (sec)</cell>
                  </row>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power Problem US Customary Units </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A worker uses a winch to lift a 200-pound load to a height of 30 feet in 2 minutes. Calculate the mechanical power in foot-pounds per minute. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical power (P) can be calculated using the formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power= <m>\frac{WorkDone}{Timerequired}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> W is the work done in foot-pounds (ft-lb) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> T is the time in minutes (min) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> First, calculate the work done (W). Work done is given by: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> W=F×d </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F is the force applied (in pounds, lb) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> D is the distance the load is lifted (in feet, ft) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Given: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> F=200 lb. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> d=30 ft </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calculate the work done (W): </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power= <m>\frac{WorkDone}{Timerequired}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em>=<m>\frac{Fxd}{t}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> W=F×d=200 lb×30 ft=6000 ft-lb </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Next, calculate the power (P): </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power (P)=<m>\frac{Work(w)}{Time(t)}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power = <m>\frac{6,000ft - lbs}{2minutes}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The mechanical power used by the winch is 3000 foot-pounds per minute (ft-lb/min). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Note that the work required is the same even with more people pulling the load. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mechanical Power Problem Metric System Units </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Given: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Force (F) =50 (Newtons) N </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Distance (d)=20 (Meters) m </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Time (t)=10 seconds (s) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Step-by-step calculation: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calculate the work done W=F⋅d=50 N×20 m=1000  </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calculate the power: Power (P)=<m>\frac{Work(w)}{Time(t)}</m> = <m>\frac{1000j}{10s}</m> =100 J/s </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> So, the mechanical power delivered by the conveyor belt is 100 joules per second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower Formula: Horsepower = <m>\frac{Work}{Timex33,000}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower may also be expressed as </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 hp = <m>\frac{33,000foot - pounds}{minute}</m> or </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 hp = <m>\frac{550foot - pounds}{second}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower Problem: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A motor exerts a force to lift a weight of 500 pounds vertically at a constant speed of 660 feet per minute. Calculate the horsepower delivered by the motor. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solution: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Recall the definition of horsepower: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 1 horsepower (hp)=33,000 foot-pounds per minute (ft-lb/min) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Given: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Force F = 500 pounds </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed = 660 feet per minute </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power in foot-pounds per minute is calculated as: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower = <m>\frac{Work}{Timex33,000}</m> = <m>\frac{Forcexdistance}{timex33,000}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <me>Horsepower = \frac{500lbsx660feet}{33,000ft - lbs/min}</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Horsepower = 10hp </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermal Power Problem in British Thermal Units (BTU’s) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>Thermal power</em> is the measure of thermal energy used per unit time. It is the rate of heat transfer or heat flow rate. Examples of thermal power units are British Thermal Units (Btu) or kilowatts (kW). Thermal power is calculated basically by the mathematical expression of: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Thermal Power<m>= \frac{HeatUsed}{TimeRequired}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P= <m>\frac{Heat}{time}</m> = <m>\frac{Q(btu's)}{t(s)}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Problem: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A heating system uses 90,000 btus of heat energy to warm a room over a period of 15 minutes. Calculate the thermal power output of the heating system in btus). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To calculate the thermal power output of the heating system, we can use the formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P= <m>\frac{Heat}{time}</m> = <m>\frac{Q(btu's)}{t(s)}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In this case: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The energy used is 90,000 BTUs. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The time period is 15 minutes. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> First, we need to convert the time period from minutes to hours since power is typically measured in BTUs per hour (BTU/hr). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 15 minutes=15/60 hours=0.25 hours </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Now, we can calculate the power: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power=90,000 BTUs/0.25 hours​ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power=360,000 BTU/hr </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> So, the thermal power output of the heating system is 360,000 BTU/hr. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Electric Power Problem in Watts </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> When dealing with electrical power, it's essential to consider the relationship between power, voltage, and current, which is given by the formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em>=<em>VI</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>P</em> is power in watts (W) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>V</em> is voltage in volts (V) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <em>I</em> is current in amperes (A) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Problem: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> An electric heater has a resistance of 10 ohms and is connected to a 120-volt power supply. Calculate the electrical power consumed by the heater in watts. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solution: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Electrical power (P) can be calculated using Ohm's law and the power formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P=​ <m>\frac{V^{2}}{R}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> where: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P is the power in watts (W) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> V is the voltage in volts (V) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> R is the resistance in ohms (Ω) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Given: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> V=120 V </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> R=10 Ω </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> First, substitute the given values into the formula: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P= ​ <m>\frac{V^{2}}{R}</m> P=​ <m>\frac{120^{2}}{10\Omega}</m>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> P= <m>\frac{14400v}{10\Omega}</m> = 1440 watts (W) </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Answer: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The electrical power consumed by the heater is 1440 watts (W). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power is expressible also as the product of the <em>force</em> applied to move an object and the speed of the object in the direction of the force. If the magnitude of the force <em>F</em> is measured in pounds and the speed <em>ν</em> in feet per minute, the power equals <em>Fν</em> foot-pounds per minute. In the <em>International System of Units</em>, power is measured in <em>newton</em> meters per second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Most machines have rotating <em>shafts</em>, and, in terms of the twisting moment, or magnitude of <em>torque</em> (τ), on a shaft and the angular speed ω of the shaft, the power is given by τω. τ is usually expressed in inch-pounds, ω in radians per second, and power in inch-pounds per second. Another unit of mechanical power is the <em>horsepower</em> (hp), which is equal to 33,000 foot-pounds per minute, or 6,600 inch-pounds per second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Instruments Used to Measure Power: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamometer: an instrument used to measure torque and power output of engines, motors, and other rotating machinery. By measuring the torque and rotational speed, the dynamometer can calculate the power output of the system. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Power Meter: an electronic device used to measure electrical power consumption. It is commonly used to monitor and optimize the energy usage of electrical devices and systems. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nautical-Specific Power Measurements </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In the nautical world, power measurements are crucial for marine engineering, ship propulsion, and navigation. Two nautical-specific power measurements are: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Propulsion Power: Propulsion power refers to the power required to drive a ship or boat through water. It is a key parameter in designing efficient propulsion systems and optimizing fuel consumption for maritime vessels. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Dynamic Positioning Power: Dynamic positioning (DP) systems are used on ships and offshore platforms to maintain their position without anchoring. The power required for DP operations is a critical consideration in offshore engineering projects. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Understanding the concept of power and its measurement is vital in your journey as engineering students. It will empower you to design energy-efficient systems, optimize power consumption, and contribute to sustainable engineering practices both on land and at sea. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed measures how fast an object is moving through a distance, and it is calculated by the formula 𝑆=𝑑𝑡, where <em>S</em> stands for speed, <em>d</em> stands for distance, and <em>t</em> stands for time. This formula calculates the average speed of a movement, and refers to the rate at which an object moves or operates. It is a measure of how quickly something changes position or performs a function over a given period. Speed is a scalar quantity, meaning it has magnitude but no direction. It is usually expressed in units of distance per unit time, such as meters per second (m/s), kilometers per hour (km/h), or miles per hour (mph). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed and velocity are terms that are often used interchangeably. However, in scientific and educational contexts the differences between them tend to be highlighted. This happens because they are two different types of quantities. While speed is a scalar quantity, velocity is a vector. Speed is defined only by its intensity (or magnitude), while velocity needs to have both magnitude and direction addressed. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The concept of speed is better understood when contrasted with the concept of velocity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed is a measurement of how fast an object is moving through a path. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Velocity measures how fast and to what direction is the movement of an object. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The symbols for speed and velocity differ by the letters used and the notation that represents the type of quantity they are. While velocity is usually symbolized by the letter <em>v</em> with an overwritten arrow (𝑣→), one can find speed being symbolized by its full name ('speed') or by its first letter (<em>S</em>). The lack of an arrow over this symbol is an indication that speed is a scalar quantity. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Types of speed </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Linear Speed: The rate at which an object moves along a path in a straight line. It is calculated as the distance traveled divided by the time taken. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speed=Distance/Time​ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Rotational Speed (Angular Speed): The rate at which an object rotates or spins. It is measured in terms of the angle turned per unit time, such as radians per second (rad/s) or revolutions per minute (RPM). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Angular Speed=Angle/Time​ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Average Speed: The total distance traveled divided by the total time taken, without regard to variations in speed during the trip. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Average Speed=Total Distance/Total Time​ </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption/>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image34.jpeg"/>
               <!-- d X t graph.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <table>
               <title/>
               <tabular>
                  <row/>
               </tabular>
            </table>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The graph shows that the object covers 20 meters in 25 seconds. Therefore, its average speed is: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑆𝑝𝑒𝑒𝑑=𝑑𝑡=2025=0.8𝑚/𝑠 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Instantaneous Speed: The speed of an object at a specific moment in time. It can be found using calculus by taking the derivative of the position with respect to time. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Flow Speed: In fluid dynamics, the speed at which a fluid flows through a pipe or channel. It is critical for calculating parameters such as Reynolds number and flow rate. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Mach Number: In aeronautical engineering, the speed of an object compared to the speed of sound in the surrounding medium. A Mach number less than 1 indicates subsonic speed, while a Mach number greater than 1 indicates supersonic speed. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Units of Speed </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Metric System: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Centimeters per second (cm/s): Occasionally used for smaller-scale measurements, particularly in scientific contexts. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Meters per second (m/s): This is the standard SI unit for speed. It indicates the number of meters traveled in one second. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Kilometers per hour (km/h): This unit is often used for measuring the speed of vehicles and other modes of transportation. It indicates the number of kilometers traveled in one hour. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> US Customary System </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Miles per hour (mph): Commonly used in the United States and the United Kingdom for measuring the speed of vehicles. It indicates the number of miles traveled in one hour. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Feet per second (ft/s): Sometimes used in various engineering contexts, especially in the United States. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nautical Units: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knots (kn or kt): Used in maritime and aviation contexts, a knot is equal to one nautical mile per hour (1 nautical mile = 1.852 kilometers). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nautical-Specific Speed Measurements: In the nautical realm, measuring speed is crucial for marine navigation and engineering. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Knot: A knot is a unit of speed used primarily in navigation and marine contexts. One knot represents one nautical mile per hour (nautical mile is approximately 1.15 statute miles). Ships and boats often use knots to measure their speed over water. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Rotational Speed: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Revolutions per minute (RPM): Used to measure the number of complete rotations or cycles per minute. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Radians per second (rad/s): Used in engineering to measure angular speed </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Various instruments are used to measure speed, depending on the context and type of speed being measured. Here are some common instruments: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Speedometer: Commonly found in vehicles, it measures the speed of the vehicle in units such as kilometers per hour (km/h) or miles per hour (mph). Instruments, such as the speedometer, can display the instantaneous speed of a vehicle. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Radar Gun: Often used by law enforcement to measure the speed of moving vehicles. It works by emitting radio waves and measuring the Doppler shift of the reflected waves. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Lidar (Light Detection and Ranging): Uses laser pulses to measure the distance to an object and can determine its speed by analyzing the time it takes for the laser to return. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pedometer: Measures the number of steps taken and can estimate speed based on stride length and the number of steps per minute. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> GPS (Global Positioning System): Uses satellite signals to determine the position of an object over time, calculating speed based on changes in position. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure>
               <caption>Speedometer showing an instantaneous speed of 172.1 Km/h.</caption>
               <image width="50%" source="images/image35.jpeg"/>
               <!--Speedometer showing an instantaneous speed of 172.1 Km/h.-->
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For Measuring Rotational Speed: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Tachometer: Measures the rotational speed of a shaft or disk, typically in revolutions per minute (RPM). </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Stroboscope: Uses flashing light to measure rotational speed by making a rotating object appear stationary when the light flashes at the same frequency as the rotation. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Optical Encoders: Detect rotational position and speed by using light and photodetectors to measure the movement of a patterned disk. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For Measuring Flow Speed: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Pitot Tube: Used in aerodynamics and fluid dynamics to measure the flow speed of air or fluid by comparing static and dynamic pressures. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Anemometer: Measures wind speed, commonly used in meteorology and environmental studies. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Flowmeter: Measures the speed and volume of fluid flowing through a pipe. Types include ultrasonic, electromagnetic, and turbine flowmeters. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> For Measuring Instantaneous Speed: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Accelerometer: Measures acceleration, which can be integrated over time to determine changes in speed. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Photo Gates: Used in physics experiments to measure the speed of an object passing through two points with a known distance apart. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Specialized Instruments: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Laser Doppler Velocimeter (LDV): Uses laser beams to measure the velocity of particles in a fluid, often used in fluid mechanics research. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Doppler Radar: Measures the speed of precipitation particles in meteorology to determine wind speeds and storm movement. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Each of these instruments is designed for specific applications and provides accurate measurements within its intended range and context. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Magnetic Speed Pickup Transducer </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The magnetic speed pickup transducer is usually referred to as a magnetic speed pickup and is the most common type of speed sensor found in gas turbine propulsion plants. It is used for sensing gas turbine speed on the LM2500 and the Allison 501-K17. It is also used to measure reduction gear speed for controllable pitch <em>propeller</em> (CPP) systems on the FFG-7 class ships. The MRGs of the DD-963 class ships use magnetic speed pickups for sensing clutch engagement speeds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Magnetic speed pickups sense speed by using a toothed gear that cuts the magnetic field of the pickup. The output of the sensor is a square-wave ac voltage. This voltage is converted to a proportional dc voltage in a signal conditioner. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Example 1: How to Calculate the Speed of an Object </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> The procedure to show how to calculate the speed of an object is straightforward. In simple problems, distance and time are given, and one only needs to execute their division. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Calculate the speed of a car that crosses a 200-meter bridge in 10 seconds. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Solution: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 𝑆=𝑑𝑡=200𝑚10𝑠=20𝑚/𝑠 </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> In some situations, the formula can be used to find: </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Distance: when speed and time values are given, the formula can be applied as 𝑑<em>=</em>𝑆∗𝑡<em>.</em>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Time: when speed and distance are given, the formula can be applied as 𝑡<em>=</em>𝑑𝑆<em>.</em>
            </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
   </folder>
</folder>
